<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The sinne of blasphemie against the Holy Ghost, scholastically examined the reasons of the absolute irremissibility thereof displayed; an admonition to all reuolting apostataes [sic] annexed. By Iohn Meredyth, sub-deane of Chichester.</title>
            <author>Meredith, John, b. 1579 or 80.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 178 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07445</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17831</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120673</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855868</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855868</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21376</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07445)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21376)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1028:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The sinne of blasphemie against the Holy Ghost, scholastically examined the reasons of the absolute irremissibility thereof displayed; an admonition to all reuolting apostataes [sic] annexed. By Iohn Meredyth, sub-deane of Chichester.</title>
                  <author>Meredith, John, b. 1579 or 80.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 70, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Edward Allde] for Iohn Marriot, and are to bee solde at his shop in St. Dunstons Church-yard in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: A-K⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sin, Unpardonable --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21376:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21376:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SINNE OF BLASPHEMIE AGAINST THE HOLY GHOST, Scholaſtically examined; the <hi>reaſons of the abſolute Irremiſsibility</hi> thereof diſplayed; An admonition <hi>to all Reuolting Apoſtataes</hi> annexed.</p>
            <p>By IOHN MEREDYTH, Sub-Deane of <hi>Chicheſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Mark. 3. Verſ. 29.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>He that Blaſphemeth againſt the Holy Ghoſt, ſhall neuer haue forgiueneſſe, but is culpable of Eternall damnation.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Heb. 10. Verſ. 38.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now the Iuſt ſhall liue by Faith, but if any withdraw himſelfe, my Soule ſhall haue no pleaſure in him.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Aug. Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Trinit. Cap.</hi> 1.</bibl>
               <p>Magis amabo inſpici a rectis, quam timebo morderi a peruerſis; Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantér enim ſuſcipit ofculum Columbinu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pulcherrima &amp; caſtiſſima charitas, dentem veró caninum euitat cautiſſima humilitas, vel re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tundit Solidi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ima veritas; Magiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> optabo, a quolibet reprehendi, quam ſiue ab Errante, ſiue ab Adulante laudari.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON. Printed for <hi>Iohn Marriot,</hi> and are to bee ſolde at his Shop in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Dunſtons</hi> Church-yard in Fleetſtreet. 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21376:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21376:2"/>
            <head>TO THE REVEREND, RIGHT LEARNED, and RELIGIOVS PRELATE, Doctor THORNE, Deane of <hi>Chicheſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was my naturall Loue, and affection to my natiue Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, (right worthy Sir) and to the Church of CHRIST in theſe parts, which ſince the time of my ſetled reſidence hereabouts, inuited me in the performance of the worke of my Miniſtery, to ſtrike at the chiefe aduerſary, who though he bee branded euen in his forehead, <note place="margin">Gal. 1. 8. 9. 1. Cor. 16.22,</note> with an <hi>Anathema</hi> yet doth he ſtill ſecretly ſeduce from vs, and carry with him to perdition no ſmall number, and is like (vnleſſe your vigilancy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent it) to preuaile further. <hi>Serpit, &amp; ſerpet hoc</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Cic. Epiſt. Tam.</note> 
               <hi>malum longiùs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was your zealous authority which indulged
<pb facs="tcp:21376:3"/>
my ſafe conduct to that ſacred place in your Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrall Church, whence ſhortly after (but at ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall times) I deliuered this ſubſequent Treatiſe; the ſubiect whereof is that dreadfull Sinne <hi>againſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mat. 12.31.32 Mark. 3.29. Luk 12 10. Heb. 6.4.5.6. Heb. 10.26.27 1. Ioh. 5.16.</note> 
               <hi>the holy Ghoſt,</hi> to terrifie all ſuch who are vpon eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry becke of the Aduerſary as ready to excurre, and runne out from vs, as hee is to inueigle them to ioyne with him, and moſt virulently to blaſpheme that truth, which eftſoone they profeſſed.</p>
            <p>In regard of which premiſſes, of Duty partly, partly of Preſumption, I doe conſecrate theſe my labours vnto your Name, intruding (as it were) vpon you for Protection, to enſconce me againſt the vilification of all Hicke-ſcorners, that hauing learned <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> aſſume the office of <note place="margin">Guil. Budaeus praeſat in Come<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> Momus vnto them, taking it as a great grace (God wot) to diſgrace thoſe, whoſe worth they may rather enuy then imirate.</p>
            <p>Theſe are thoſe Eyes (forſooth) and Ouer-ſeers of other, of whom Gods Church may iuſtly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, <hi>Contenebrati ſunt oculi mei,</hi> yea happy were hee, were ſhee deliuered of ſuch Eyes, which as the Prophet ſpeakes, <hi>Nihilreſpiciunt niſimalae.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ren.</hi> 5. <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bakkuk.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>To whom then in this caſe ſhould I breake my ſelfe in theſe parts? but to your ſelfe, which I doe: <hi>Rumpantur vt ilia Coaro,</hi> Aske of Religion (faith <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Virg. Bacol.</note> the ſonne of <hi>Syrach)</hi> of him that hath Religion; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccluſ.</hi> 37.11.</note> of a matter of Learning of him that hath learning: as for any blinde <hi>Ariſtarchus</hi> or his buzzardly broode, who ſhall preſumptuouſly ſmite the Law, and diffame the Doctors thereof; and flaunder
<pb facs="tcp:21376:3"/>
his Mothers own Sonnes, what haue I, or indeed, what hath the Spirit of God to doe with them?</p>
            <p>They occaſion the Aduerſaries of the Truth to perfiſt in Haereſie, yea through their Iudaicall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarication, ſome Citizens of Faith (as they ſeemed ſometime) with a <hi>Nolumus hunc regnare ſuper nos,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Luk. 19.</note> caſt off the yoake alſo.</p>
            <p>If any friend them, I recken them as did <hi>Clement</hi> in the number of thoſe, <hi>Qui exterminare volunt Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Diſt.</hi> 93, <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Det,</hi> I for my part, I confidently proſeſſe, I paſſe not for them; yea I proclaime my ſelfe a mortall enemy for Gods cauſe, vnto ſuch men; <hi>Semper metales inſequanter hoſtes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Vnto thee therefore (the Reſplendent Starre of <note place="margin">Joh. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Hebr. Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a.</note> this Climate) doe I flie for Patronage, as to a man for thine incomparable skill in the Orientall ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred <note place="margin">D. Pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tr. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. H. G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>frey Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Joh. Dr. in libr. praeterit. pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t. Vita &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Ioh. Dr. Abo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Cur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>andro Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thore.</note> tongues on this ſide; and beyond the Seas, by men vnmatchable therein moſt worthily fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſed, as to a man, both in <note n="*" place="margin">See his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or Behold the man to King Iames.</note> Diuine and Humane literature more profound (which ſhall I ſay) or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquent. As to a man for thy piety to God, thy Charity to men, and aboue all, thy moſt prouident feruentzeale, in preſeruing the Poſſeſſions, Immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, &amp; Priuiledges of that little <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 19.20.22</note> Segor (that Sea Church I meane) which thou doſt now illuſtrate condignly renowned; In a word, to one for that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>His Tuilius</hi> or <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> to the Earle of Pem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brooke.</note> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 15. 16.17</note> Chriſts triple <hi>Paſch</hi> well known to all, <hi>Virtus Vlyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi> (I will vſurpe that of <hi>Seneca)</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>nota Donais eſt ſatis, Nimiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Phrigibus.</hi> To conclude, I ſubiect this Tractate to the Cenſure of the Church, and your worthy ſelfe; which I doe not publiſh (I proteſt)
<pb facs="tcp:21376:4"/>
for any oſtentation, much leſſe for any purpoſe to detract from the labours of other more learned Diuines, (whom I cannot neuertheleſſe acquit from deficience, and error in this argument) nor doe I obtrude it on the world as a new Article of Faith, to oblige Conſciences; for by experience in my ſelfe, and obſeruation in other, I finde it to be moſt true, which that great light of Phyſitians ſpake of <hi>Archigenes</hi> his error, as elegantly as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly, <note place="margin">Galen. lib. de Compoſit. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicament. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 2<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</note> ſaying: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp;c. It is a hard matter for him that is but a man, not to erre in many thinges, as being only ſciolous in ſome, miſpriſioning other, &amp; wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting alſo, and publiſhing ſome things incuriouſly.</p>
            <p>But from the firſt birth of it I intended the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke benefit of the Church of Chriſt, that is; That Apoſtataes might bee recalled, terrified, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, wauering or doubtfull Chriſtians might be confirmed or reeſtabliſhed, our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour IESVS CHRIST might by his Goſpell bee glorified, now and euermore. So be it.</p>
            <p>So fare thee well, thou rich Ornament of <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter</hi> poore Church.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>To your Reuerence, the moſt Deuoted: IOHN MERIDTYH.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21376:4"/>
            <head>To the Indifferent Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Ood Reader, as wee are obliged by Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian modeſty to Beleeue the principles of Faith, before wee preſume to diſcuſſe them by reaſon; So I hold it Negligence, if after our confirmation in the Faith, we ſtudy not to vnderſtand the reaſon of that we beleeue. In which conſideration, I (though the weakeſt among thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands) am excited, to wade into theſe depthes, where (as <note n="*" place="margin">Ad Leandr, de Expoſitione libri Job.</note> 
               <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith) <hi>Agnus peditet, &amp; Elephas natet,</hi> the ſimple may finde what to learne, and the learned what to admire as In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>omprehenſible.</p>
            <p>Wherein, if (by Gods aſsiſtance) I doe happily finde ought, whereof before I was ignorant, I doe willingly impart the ſame vnto others; <hi>Apertae Muſaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ianuae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The vnſtable diſſoluteneſſe of ſundry deboſhed Var<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, in this decrepit Age of the world wherein wee liue, who halting betweene two opinions, ſpare not to belch forth blaſphemies againſt the Truth, whereof they are aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, hath mooued mee to ſearch into that fearefull <hi>Sinne</hi> of <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> that thoſe who repute it a ſmall matter, to depart from the Truth of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> to the Tents of <hi>Antechriſt,</hi> may conſider the danger, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, before they fall into that <hi>Sinne</hi> againſt the <hi>Holy Ghoſt, which is Irrecouerable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21376:5"/>
Againe the tender Conſciences of other, who capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uated with a conceit of this Sinne, haue beene ſwallowed vp in Deſpaire. How neceſſary the Subject is, I referre to thy Iudgement; In the meane time I feare, that leaſt as Painters, who limbe a ſatre creature in vgly forme, deſerue iuſt rebuke: So I ſhould drawe on my ſelfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued reproach, by cloathing ſo wrothy a matter, in a rude and vnpoliſhed ſtile.</p>
            <p>Tet this may not with-hold mee; for I binde no man from more curious performance hereof, whom my harſh phraſe offendeth: But this I craue; If any ſuppoſe that I haue ſet abroath herein, any thing different from the Truth, let him not preſently condemnt me, as a preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous publiſher of Nouelties, or a broacher of falſhood, vntill he hath firſt conſulted with the Authors herein alledged.</p>
            <p>Howſoeuer, if I haue not attained my purpoſe herein, yet I reioyce in ſeeking laboriouſly; though the length and difficulty of the way cauſe me to faile:</p>
            <p>This I am ſure, I may truely ſay; I haue done my vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt: I haue ſought, if not ſound; I haue called, if not receaued an anſwer.</p>
            <p>Take it (gentle Reader) as it is, if it anſwer my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, it cannot diſpleaſe thee; Howeuer, I publiſh it, to Gods glory, and thy good.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in Christ Iesvs, John Meredyth.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21376:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Sinne</hi> OF BLASPHEMIE againſt the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> Schola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtically examined; the reaſons of the <hi>abſolute Irremiſsibility</hi> thereof diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>played; An admonition to all <hi>Reuolting Apoſtataes</hi> annexed.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>HEB. CAP. 3. VER. 26.</bibl>
               <q>For if wee Sinne wilfully, after wee haue receiued the knowledge of the Truth, there remaineth no more Sacrifice for Sinne.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Scripture, is one of thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whence certaine of the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epipha. lib. z. cont. haer. tom.</hi> 1. <hi>haeres.</hi> 59.</note> 
               <hi>Aunti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,</hi> tooke occaſion to improue the authority of this <hi>Epiſtle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence was it, that <hi>Nouatus</hi> the <hi>Cathariſt,</hi> laboured to maintaine that mercileſſe poſition, <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cyprian. Epiſt. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 23.</note> That whoſoeuer had once after <hi>Baptiſme</hi> fallen into perſecution, though af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward he praeſented himſelfe before the throne of Gods grace, with fountaines of teares, yet had hee the Gates of his mercy ſhut vp againſt him for euer.</p>
            <p>Hence is that, which M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Inſtitut. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 3.21.</note> 
               <hi>Caluin</hi> obſerued; that <hi>Quidam boni viri, hanc ſuppoſititiam Epiſtolam crediderunt;</hi> That certaine worthy men, (ſpeaking of ſome of his owne time) being offended at the roughnes &amp; auſterity of this Doctrine,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21376:6"/>
admitted not this <hi>Epiſtle</hi> as <hi>Authenticall,</hi> when as notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, the profound Myſteries, and impregnable argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments therein contained, doe maintain, <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Theophilact. in expoſ. verſ.</hi> 3 <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. <hi>ad Hebr.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nullius alterius eſſe poſſe niſi Pauli;</hi> that it can be fathered vpon none other but S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul,</hi> in whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe ſpake.</p>
            <p>Wherefore that all occaſion of doubt and obſcurity may be remoued, which partly crept vp by Abuſe; partly for want and neglect of that due reſpect, which ought to haue beene had, vnto that dependency, which theſe wordes haue on the pręcedent, (without which) they cannot be read vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any true ſence in themſelues; I will diſplay the ſcope and drift of the Author in this Epiſtle.</p>
            <p>Whoſe generall intention is, to ſet forth and declare vnto vs, the Dignity and Excellency of our Sauiour <hi>Chriſt;</hi> the Sufficiency of the Goſpell, and the Inſufficiency of the Law.</p>
            <p>And to this end, he diuideth his Epiſtle into foure parts; In the firſt, hee ſheweth the Excellency of our Sauiour, by comparing him, (but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) by way of pręheminence and ſuperiority; Firſt with the Prophets; Secondly with the Angels; Thirdly with <hi>Moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s;</hi> Fourthly (by way of Alluſion) vnto the Leuiticall Prieſthood: and this, in the firſt ſeauen Chapters of this Epiſtle.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by way of recapitulation, of certaine pointes premiſed in the former Chapters; he doth more at large ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the Inſufficiency of the Lawe, and that by comparing it; Firſt, with the <hi>New Teſtament;</hi> Secondly, by the figure of the <hi>Tabernacle;</hi> Thirdly, by the conditions of the <hi>Legall Sacrifice;</hi> and this from the beginning of the Eight Chapter, vnto the nineteenth Verſe of the tenth Chapter.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, out of the former Doctrine, he draweth certaine morall precepts, which extend, vnto the 18.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Verſe of the laſt Chapter.</p>
            <p>Wherein, firſt he exhorteth them to imbrace the Goſpell; and to make his Doctrine more effectuall, and perſuaſiue, hee declareth the vtility redounding to thoſe who perſiſt therein the 23. Verſe of this Chapter.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:21376:6"/>
Secondly, hee propoundeth the dangerous and dreadfull fall of thoſe, who after they haue once beleeued it, and knowne it to be the Truth, become notwithſtanding of their owne accord, backſliding <hi>Apoſtates,</hi> and <hi>malicious Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries</hi> thereunto, and this in my Text. Wherein, I note the aggrauation of this <hi>Sinne</hi> of <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> by three Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe it proceedeth from a firme reſolution, and malitious will, and purpoſe, to Sinne in this kinde; In this word <hi>Wilfully.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe it is againſt the <hi>Euangelicall Truth,</hi> before beleeued and knowne, In theſe wordes; <hi>After wee haue receiued the knowledge of the Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, becauſe of the <hi>Inexpiability of it;</hi> In the laſt wordes; <hi>There remaineth no more Sacrifice for Sinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is no one place, in the whole body of the Holy Scripture, which doth ſo euidently explaine that dreadfull <note place="margin">Math. 12. Mark. 3. Luk. 12.</note> Sinne, ſpoken of by our Sauiour in the Goſpell, (that <hi>Sinne</hi> I meane againſt the Holy Ghoſt) with the circumſtances, and ſequell thereof, as this briefe Text, if it were throughly examined, and exactly diſcuſſed.</p>
            <p>I am (I confeſſe) in euery reſpect, vnworthy to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take a matter ſo holy, ſo indifficult, ſo Diuine, ſo farre aboue the reach of my capacity, who am euery way vnmeete to be named with thoſe, who haue laboured before mee, to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maske the face of this obſcurity.</p>
            <p>But I doe humbly beſeech the true Lord and Maſter of vs all, that hee would vouchſafe to inſtruct mee herein, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the Sacred Scriptures, or by the writings of the holy Learned, and by the Aſſiſtance of his holy Spirit; that I may ſo propound, ſo affirme; that in my aſſertions, I may alway cleaue vnto the Truth; So that what proceedeth from mee, may principally be acceptable in his ſight, and conſequently accepted by the faithfull.</p>
            <p>To enter therefore into the handling of this obſcure que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion; I obſerue theſe pointes:</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:21376:7"/>
Firſt, the <hi>diſtinct Species or kinde of Sinne,</hi> heere mentia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, In the firſt word; <hi>Sinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the <hi>Sub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ct</hi> of this <hi>Sinne: the Will, wilfully.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the <hi>Obiect,</hi> againſt which it is committed; the <hi>Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, the <hi>Circumſtances</hi> wherewith it muſt bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſted, <hi>Beleeued</hi> and <hi>knowen;</hi> in theſe wordes, <hi>After wee haue receiued the knowledge of the Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, the <hi>Sequell</hi> or <hi>Effect of it, Deſtitution of remedy:</hi> In theſe wordes, <hi>There remaineth no more Sacrifice for Sinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The diſtinct Species or kinde of this Sinne; If wee Sinne.</head>
               <p>THE terme <hi>Sinne,</hi> is vſed in the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and by <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines,</hi> in two Senſes.</p>
               <p>Sometime <hi>Generally;</hi> and ſo it expreſſeth <hi>All,</hi> or <hi>any Sinne,</hi> of what kinde ſoeuer, wherewith God is offended; as by our Sauiour it is vſed, <hi>Whoſoeuer committeth Sinne, is the Seruant of Sinne.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 8.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Somtime <hi>particularly,</hi> and for <hi>Diſtinction;</hi> and ſo it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigneth <hi>Some one Sinne,</hi> In which ſence alſo it is vſed by CHRIST, to ſpecifie to the <hi>Phariſes,</hi> their <hi>wilfull Incredu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity;</hi> If <hi>I had not come and ſpoken vnto them, they ſhould not</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 35.</note> 
                  <hi>haue had Sinne;</hi> by which ſaying, he would haue vs vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, ſaith the Father; <note n="*" place="margin">Auguſt. ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Non omne peccatum,</hi> not euery Sinne, vnder a generall terme; but <hi>Magnum quoddam pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum,</hi> one certaine great Sinne; which was, <hi>Quia non cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diderunt in eum;</hi> their non credulity, Seing CHRIST came to this end, that they ſhould beleeue in him.</p>
               <p>And in this ſence the word <hi>Sinne</hi> is heere vſed; <hi>viz.</hi> to denote a <hi>particular Sinne,</hi> namely; <hi>A totall Deſertion of the Faith of</hi> Chriſt, <hi>before receiued.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The occaſion was the Inſtability of the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> who
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21376:7"/>
ſlid backe from the Goſpell, which before they profeſſed; And in theſe wordes, the danger of ſuch Apoſtacy is expre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſed by the Apoſtle, firſt laying before them the quality of Apoſtacy, in the word, <hi>Sinne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As CHRIST came to call the world to follow him, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming life Eternall to all who beleeued in him; So hee meant, that thoſe who refuſed him, or hauing receiued him, but after departed from him, ſhould haue no part in his promiſe.</p>
               <p>For when hee ſent abroad his Diſciples, with prędiction of the Croſſe for his ſake, hee ſaid, that thoſe onely; <hi>Who</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Math. 10,</note> 
                  <hi>continued faithfull vnto the end, in bearing Witnes vnto his Name, ſhould bee ſaued;</hi> and contrarily bee by ſo much more remote from Saluation, by how many moe degrees, they ſeperated themſelues from CHRIST.</p>
               <p>But as three thinges neceſſarily concurre to make a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian;</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Faith,</hi> whereby wee beleeue in him, and aſſent to his Goſpell.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of his Name, and <hi>profeſſion</hi> of his Goſpell.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>Defence</hi> of his Name and Goſpell, and that vnto Death, if neede ſo require.</p>
               <p>So there are three Degrees, by which a man falleth away wholy from CHRIST, and vnrecouerably depriueth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe of Saluation:</p>
               <p>Firſt, by <hi>denying Chriſt or his Goſpell, againſt his Beleefe and knowledge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, by <hi>an vniuerſall Apoſtacy from Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, by <hi>Rebellion, and hate againſt Chriſt, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with all manner Impugning him, and his Goſpell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, when <hi>Gods Truth</hi> ſhall manifeſtly appeare vnto thee, ſo that thou art conuicted in thy heart and Conſcience, that the matter ſtandeth ſo, and cannot bee otherwiſe; yet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notwithſtanding, thou dareſt Impiouſly deny this Truth, affirming it not to bee of God, but of the Deuill, like the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21376:8"/>
wicked <hi>Phariſes,</hi> who againſt their Conſcience, aſcribed the manifeſt worke of GOD, to <hi>Belzebub;</hi> when as notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, they dayly perceiued ſuch thinges to haue beene done by him, which no man could effect, except God had beene with him.</p>
               <p>This is, <hi>Non videre quod videas</hi> ſaith a <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pacian. Epiſt.</hi> 3. <hi>ad Sympron. No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>at.</hi> Rom. 14.</note> Father; to ſhut thine eyes, leaſt thou ſhouldeſt ſee.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle ſaith, that <hi>Whatſoeuer is not of Faith, is Sinne,</hi> and that <hi>Priuatiuely;</hi> and therefore the <hi>Pagans,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their Ignorance, periſh; But whatſoeuer is done againſt Faith, and a good Conſcience, <hi>Poſitiuely,</hi> is the <hi>fury</hi> of <hi>Sinne,</hi> which is Irremediable; and whoſoeuer being fallen, is not raiſed againe by the Suggeſtion hereof, there is no hope of him; Seing his Conſcience, which is <hi>Inſtar mille teſtium,</hi> as ſtrong as a thouſand witneſſes, is ſeared and ſenceleſſe; for ſuch are <hi>dead while they liue; who ſeeing are blinde, and doe not ſee; hearing are deafe, and heare not the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Spirit;</hi> and ſuch renouncing CHRIST, who is the Life, ſhut vp the way, by which they ſhould returne vnto him againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Secondly a totall Apoſtacy from Chriſt.</head>
               <p>AS <hi>Sinne</hi> doth formally conſiſt, in <note n="*" place="margin">Auguſt. lib. de lib. arb.</note> 
                  <hi>auerſione ab In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commutabili bono,</hi> in turning from the vnchangeable Good; ſo there is <hi>One Sinne</hi> which ſeperateth a man wholy from God.</p>
               <p>But as Man is Ioyned vnto God, principally by <hi>Faith,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aquin.</hi> 22, 2. <hi>queſt.</hi> 12. <hi>art.</hi> 1.</note> ſo <hi>Infidelity</hi> taken contrary, for a contempt of the Faith, and Impugning the ſame; or rather that, which <hi>Bonouenturae</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Contiloq. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 26.</note> calleth <hi>Apoſtaciam perfidiae,</hi> a wilfull turning from the Faith once receiued; ſo that the party doth <hi>Male de Deo ſentire,</hi> thinke euill of God, <hi>Blaſpemare</hi> ſpeake reproachfully of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Comb. in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend. Theolog. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 6.</note> him, <hi>&amp; Sacramenta indigne tractare,</hi> ſcornfully abuſe his Sacraments, this I ſay, ſeperateth a man fartheſt from God;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21376:8"/>
So that it conſiſteth not, in any <hi>Act of Infirmity,</hi> or breach of the ſecond Table.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But in an vniuerſall Defection, and reuolting of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate from the meanes of his</hi> Saluation; <hi>Quod ex de'pera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Inſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 3. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>furore profectum</hi> (ſaith M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Caluin)</hi> the which proceeding from a deſperat fury, betokeneth the party to bee poſſeſſed by the Deuill.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, which is the greateſt Impiety of all; when the Soule is growen to that Impudence, that it laboureth by all meanes poſſible to ſubuert CHRIST and his Goſpell; ſo that now <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bernard. Ser. de</hi> 7. <hi>mrijs.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Eum paenitet adhaeſiſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Chriſto;</hi> hee grieueth that euer he followed Chriſt; and for all his ſweet Mercies, in ſteed of thankes, hee repayeth him with contumely and perſecution.</p>
               <p>Firſt, to this purpoſe, (as one <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rich. de Scto vict. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de crud. Interho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>inis Cap.</hi> 18.</note> noteth) he doth <hi>Abijcere,</hi> caſt him of, with <hi>Nolumus hunc regnare,</hi> refuſing to be any longer called a Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Obijcere,</hi> mainely oppoſe himſelfe againſt his honour.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>Deijcere,</hi> labour to ſuppreſſe his Dominion.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>Subijcere,</hi> tyranize ouer him, and trample him vnder feete.</p>
               <p>O how fearefull a caſe is it, to impugne Chriſt, who is the Truth! Such a one rideth with the Deuill, who is the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Lyes;</hi> and therefore it may well bee a Signe of one <note place="margin">Ioh. 8.</note> that poſteth to Hell; thoſe are they, who Sinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt, which neuer ſhall bee forgiuen.</p>
               <p>The which Sinne is extended by the Schoole-men vnto three Degrees: Sometime it is <hi>Conceitted in the Heart,</hi> and <note place="margin">Heb. Cap. 10. Verſ. 19.</note> there reſteth; as in thoſe, <hi>Who account the Blood of the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament as an vnholy thing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sometime it is attended with a <hi>Deteſtation of the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and breaketh into Wordes;</hi> and then with <hi>Blaſphemous mouthes they reuile the Spirit of Grace.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Verſe codem,</note>
               </p>
               <p>And at length as open Enemies to Chriſt, and his Truth; they <hi>manifeſt it in Action, Treading the Sonne of God vnder</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ibid,</note>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:21376:9"/>
                  <hi>their feete;</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle.</p>
               <p>And although the Sinne <hi>againſt the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> bee the <hi>Speaking of a word againſt him;</hi> yet it cauſeth no doubt in this point: For a man may ſpeake diuerſly; (<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Caictan. in Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ad</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">•</hi>.2. <hi>Aquin. queſt.</hi> 13. <hi>Art.</hi> 1.</note> ſaith one,) <hi>Optatiue,</hi> in heart; <hi>Enunciatiue,</hi> vocally; <hi>Imperatiue,</hi> wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully; compelling other to the like.</p>
               <p>This appeared in <hi>Iultan</hi> the <hi>Apoſtata:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hee <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Socrat. l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>br.</hi> 3. <hi>Eccl. hiſt. cap.</hi> 1.</note> ſecretly deteſted CHRIST, and imitated the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of <hi>Libanius</hi> the <hi>Sophiſt,</hi> and <hi>Maximus</hi> the <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> his Maſters, at <hi>Nicomedia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, hee vſually termed Chriſt (in contempt) <hi>Gali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laean;</hi> bellowing forth, (euen at his Death alſo) this Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy; <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Theodo. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Eccl. hiſt. cap.</hi> 25</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icifti Galilaee,</hi> thou haſt vanquiſhed mee Gali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laean.</p>
               <p>And laſtly being enraged by the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> of <hi>Antiochiae,</hi> at the <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ruſſin. libr.</hi> 1. <hi>Eccleſ. hiſt. cap.</hi> 35.36.</note> fetching home from <hi>Daphne,</hi> the Corpes of <hi>Babilas</hi> the Martyr; (whoſe propinquity ſilenced their Oracle) for that they ſang with Ioy and exultation; <hi>Let all bee confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that worſhip carued Images.</hi> He reſolued to imitate the cruelty of <hi>Diocletian</hi> againſt the Chriſtians, commaunding <hi>Saluſtius</hi> his Preſident, in the meane time to torture thoſe who did ſing at that time; And among other they afflicted <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Socrat. vbi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ra cap.</hi> 16. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17.</note> 
                  <hi>Theodorus</hi> a young man, with paines moſt cruell and of long continuance.</p>
               <p>This is the condition of the perſidious <hi>Apoſtata;</hi> for as when the life of the Body is taken away, all the Members are depriued of their due diſpoſition; So when the life of the Soule (which is Faith, as the Apoſtle ſaith) is extinguiſhed, there appeareth a diſorder in all the powers, and faculties of <note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> the ſame, and the Members of the Body; In the <hi>Heart</hi> which conceiueth hate againſt God; In the <hi>mouth</hi> which blaſphemeth him; In the <hi>Motiue Inſtruments</hi> which perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute him; So that the wordes of <hi>Salomon</hi> are verified of him: <note place="margin">Prouerb. 6.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Virnequam</hi> or <hi>Apoſtata</hi> (as the vulgar tranſlation ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it) <hi>ambulat peruerſo ore, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:21376:9"/>
                  <hi>The wicked Apostate, walketh with a froward mouth; He maketh a ſigne with his eyes, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ſignifieth with his fingers, leude thinges are in his heart, hee imagineth Euill at all times, and raiſeth vp Contentions;</hi> and his Iudgement is annexed; <hi>Therefore ſhall his deſtruction come ſodainly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out recouery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To deny him, were with the <hi>Greekes,</hi> to repute him <hi>foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhnes,</hi> and argueth damnable pride; To renounce him; whoſe ſeruice would yeeld thee a Kingdome aeternall, were <hi>monſtrous Ingratitude;</hi> But if farther, thou doeſt calumni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate and reuile him Opprobriouſly and falſely, either by vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt Detraction, or imputation, or labour to ruinate his Kingdome by perſecution, thou art a <hi>Blaſphemer, and Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt againſt the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Subiect of this Sinne, The Will, Wilfully.</head>
               <p>MAN being created by GOD, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Benanent. Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uilo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. pt.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Vt ageret opera ſua a Deo, ſecundum Deum &amp; propter Deum:</hi> to performe his actions by the power of Gods might, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Direction of his wiſedome, and to the aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Glory; had for the full and perfect execution hereof, his Soule endowed with three principall faculties, termed by the School-men, <hi>Actuum humanorum principia.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aquin.</hi> 12. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 78. <hi>art.</hi> 1. <hi>Compend. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>b.</hi> 2. <hi>Cap.</hi> 49.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt, is <hi>Voluntas;</hi> the <hi>Will,</hi> by <hi>Albertus</hi> termed <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ix potentia,</hi> the commaunding power; The Second, <hi>Intellectus;</hi> the vnderſtanding; termed <hi>Conſultrix potentia,</hi> the aduiſing or directing power; The Third, <hi>Appe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itus ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitiuus</hi> the Appetite Senſitiue, termed <hi>Affectiua potentia</hi> the deſiring power.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Will,</hi> was giuen as a powerfull Potentate, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the whole Man to the will of his Maker; But foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, as this could not bee effected, vnleſſe the will of God, were firſt made knowne vnto her; therefore the <hi>Vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> was giuen, to enlighten with the manifeſt knowledge of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21376:10"/>
the firſt <hi>Truth;</hi> and the <hi>Vertue appetitiue,</hi> which could not bee ſatisfied, but with the perfect loue of the <hi>chiefe Good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But through <hi>Adams</hi> Sinne, the powers of the Soule, were ſo peruerted and crazed; Euen as an Inſtrument of Muſick, which when it is crackt and out of Tune, in ſteed of ſweete Melody, annoyeth the Eare with harſh ſound.</p>
               <p>Hence commeth it to paſſe, that the <hi>Will,</hi> before ſo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in her command, and abſolute in Dominion ouer Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and Carnall concupiſcence, findeth in her kingdome, ſo many Contradictions, Rebellions, Conflictations, Contrarie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Oppoſitions. Briefely, herſelfe to bee infected with <hi>Malice,</hi> prone vnto euill, ouer-ruled by <hi>Senſuality,</hi> and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by drawne vnto Carnall deſires.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Vnderſtanding,</hi> which was ſo prudent an informing Counſailour vnto the will, is ſo blinded with <hi>Ignorance,</hi> that it cannot diſcerne the Truth, but is quickly deceiued, and prone vnto Error.</p>
               <p>And the <hi>Appetite Senſitiue,</hi> before, a prouident and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Subiect, is now infected with Infirmity and concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence, rebellious againſt reaſon, and inclining vnto all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of euill, kindling in vs, an vnceſſant deſire to Sinne.</p>
               <p>All, whatſoeuer Sinnes, proceed from a corruption in one of theſe principall faculties;</p>
               <p>Sometime, by default of the <hi>Vertue Appetitiue;</hi> when we fall into Sinnes through <hi>Infirmity,</hi> and notwithſtanding all our reſiſtance, wee cannot fully auoyde them; but with Humiliation wee acknowledge them, and accuſe our ſelues for the Commiſſion.</p>
               <p>Sometime by default of <hi>vnderſtanding;</hi> when we incurre ſinnes through <hi>error,</hi> and commit euill, becauſe we thinke it to be good; being deceiued by the vayle of a falſe opinion, which cauſeth in vs deniall of thoſe ſinnes.</p>
               <p>Sometime by default of the <hi>will;</hi> when we commit ſinnes of meere iniquity; knowing them, being able to reſiſt them, and yet of purpoſe committing them; with <hi>contumacie</hi> in the <hi>commiſſion, contempt</hi> of God in the <hi>tranſgreſſion,</hi> and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21376:10"/>
                  <hi>impudence</hi> in the <hi>factitation</hi> of them; Such are ſaid to be <hi>ſinnes of malice:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In which ſence, the word <hi>wilfully,</hi> is vſed in my Text; and ſo much the Greeke Aduerbe ſoundeth, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> voluntarily, wittingly, and of ſet purpoſe, without any compulſion;</p>
               <p>And in this ſence, <hi>Aquine</hi> expoundeth the Latine word <hi>voluntary</hi> in my Text, for the <hi>deliberate malice of the will,</hi> diſtinguiſhing it from <hi>volens,</hi> which ſignifieth a ſeduction through paſſion, without obſtinacie.</p>
               <p>For a man may ſinne in blaſphemy againſt God, by <hi>feare, compulſion,</hi> and <hi>conſtraint,</hi> drawne vnto it by the <hi>infirmity</hi> of the fleſh, which declineth the horrour of torments; as did S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>concil. conc. Synueſſae.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Marcellinus Biſhop of Rome,</hi> and many other in the Primitiue Church, who notwithſtanding did after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and became glorious Martyrs, of whom ſaith that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Martyr, &amp; <note n="*" place="margin">Cyprian. Ser. de Lapſis.</note> Biſhop of <hi>Carthage, Non animus ſed cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus in dolore defecit;</hi> the fleſh fainted, but their heart did not vtterly faile vnder thoſe tortures.</p>
               <p>Or thus may a man ſinne of <hi>ignorance,</hi> as many of the <hi>Iewes</hi> did, when they paſſed by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and nodded their <note place="margin">Math. 27.</note> heads at him in deriſion, as he did hang on the Croſſe; and as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> did, who perſecuted Chriſt, <hi>ignorantly, and through</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>vnbeliefe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Or thus may a man ſinne of <hi>malice</hi> and <hi>wilfully,</hi> of meere hate againſt Chriſt, with a full purpoſe to ſinne in this kinde, without any outward cauſe mouing thereunto, but <hi>ex indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria,</hi> as the Schoolemen ſpeake, with earneſt deſire to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it, and without all coaction; for ſeeing, that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is <hi>voluntary</hi> is cauſed, either <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bonauent. part.</hi> 3. <hi>Breuil. cap.</hi> 11.</note> 
                  <hi>per violentiam,</hi> or <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantiam,</hi> by violence, or ignorance: The firſt for want of <hi>power,</hi> the ſecond by defect of knowledge; when the <hi>will</hi> is ſo corrupt, that though it could reſiſt, and likewiſe did know the ſinne, being not drawne vnto it, by any <hi>paſſion</hi> or <hi>infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity</hi> in the <hi>appetite ſenſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iue</hi> or <hi>error</hi> in <hi>reaſon,</hi> or the <hi>vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding;</hi> but performe it <hi>Elicite a ſe,</hi> immediatly from it ſelfe; <hi>Ibi ineſt plen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſima ratio peccati</hi> ſaith <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Scotus ſuper</hi> 2. <hi>Sent. diſt.</hi> 43.</note> one, It is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21376:11"/>
of ſinne; this is, <hi>peccare ex certa malitia</hi> ſay the Schoole-men, To ſinne of <hi>ſet malice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To the farther vnderſtanding whereof; know, that malice in the will,</hi> hath it's degrees.</p>
               <p>The firſt kinde is <hi>ſimple malice,</hi> a taynt of originall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bonauent ſuper</hi> 2. <hi>Sent. diſt.</hi> 43.</note> from which no man is wholy quit.</p>
               <p>Sometime is ioyned hereunto, an <hi>actuall peruerſity of the will;</hi> and this is termed <hi>certa malitia,</hi> ſet malice.</p>
               <p>A man may ſinne of <hi>ſet malice,</hi> two wayes. <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Aquin. ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, ſecundae q.</hi> 13. <hi>art.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, by the inclination of a <hi>vitious habite;</hi> and this is a generall condition of ſinne.</p>
               <p>Secondly, when a man runneth on to ſinne, <hi>ſub ratione peccati,</hi> ſaith <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Jac. Almayn. moral cap.</hi> 27.</note> 
                  <hi>Aquine;</hi> becauſe it is ſinne; and that, <hi>quia of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſiuum Dei</hi> ſaith another; becauſe it offendeth God: And this is the higheſt height of <hi>iniquity;</hi> which if it be ioyned to <hi>Apostacie</hi> from <hi>Chriſt;</hi> the ſinner doth <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. praefat. in Epiſt. ad Rom.</hi> Pro. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>ſciens peccatum in Spiritum Sanctum committere;</hi> wittingly commit that ſinne againſt the <hi>Holy Ghoſt;</hi> and ſuch doe, <hi>laetaeri cum malefece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint,</hi> reioyce and take pleaſure in doing it: ſo that <hi>malice</hi> is in the ſpirit of ſuch, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bonauent. vbi ſupra.</hi> Math. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>ſecundum ſe, ſubiectiuely,</hi> which our Sauiour termeth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the <hi>blaſphemie of the Spirit;</hi> which words an ancient Diuine expounding, ſaith, it is, <hi>Affectus &amp; deſiderium vituperationis diuinae;</hi> a ſtrong <note place="margin">Rich. de Sancts' vict. tract. de Spi. blaſp.</note> deſire to diffame God; And <note n="*" place="margin">Bucan.</note> another expoundeth it more familiarly, <hi>Blaſphemia ſpiritus, in ſpiritum; Actiuely</hi> and <hi>paſſiuely;</hi> the blaſphemy of the <hi>ſpirit of man,</hi> againſt the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God;</hi> and * <hi>Caietane</hi> accordeth; <hi>Maligna machinatio aduerſus Deum;</hi> a malicious intention againſt God. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ientac.</hi> 8, <hi>q.</hi> 1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>So that the <hi>malice of the will</hi> is the <hi>formall,</hi> diſtinguiſhing it from all other ſinnes.</p>
               <p>A dreadfull caſe, when a man is growne to that height of malice, that he ſhould take pleaſure in diſgracing God; and this is true blaſphemy.</p>
               <p>I beleeue the iudgement of <hi>Richardus; Quid eſt blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia? niſi vituperatio diuina;</hi> Blaſphemy is nought elſe, but, <note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi ſupra.</note> a diſpraſing of God; the word ſoundeth the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:21376:11"/>
It may ſeeme ſtrange, and happily incredible to ſome, that any ſhould be ſo peruerſe; but let thoſe who are ſo concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, heare what Chriſt ſpeaketh of ſuch perſons; <hi>New haue</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>they hated me, and my father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hence it came to paſſe, that the <hi>blaſphemous Phariſies,</hi> who were ſuch perſons, would haue falſly faſtned on Chriſt this diſhonour, that hee had <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, an vncleane <note place="margin">Mar. 3.</note> ſpirit.</p>
               <p>I am of this opinion that no ſinne, be it neuer ſo haynous, is that <hi>ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> vnleaſt it proceede from the <hi>malice of the will,</hi> as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>And againe, I ſuppoſe, that in whomſoeuer this <hi>malice</hi> of the <hi>will</hi> doth remaine; in him alſo, is that <hi>euill and vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>heart, to depart away from the liuing God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therfore though one ſhould baptize an Image, adore the deuill, ſcorne the bleſſed Sacrament, turne Turke, or commit other moſt horrible ſinnes, either for gaine, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he would know ſome ſecret from the diuel, or through madnes or feare; ſo that it be not done of <hi>wilfull malice againſt God,</hi> it maketh not guilty of this ſinne, though other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, it make him an haynous ſinner.</p>
               <p>So that wee may vſurpe the words of <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>retract. cap.</hi> 15.</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> for a concluſion of this point; That now the <hi>will,</hi> is principall (if not totall) Actorheerein; <hi>Vſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> adeo peccatum eſt, vt ſinon eſſet voluntarium, non eſſet peccatum;</hi> It is ſo farre forth a ſinne againſt the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> that were it not <hi>maliciouſly wilfull,</hi> it were not a ſinne of this kinde; for this malice di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly impugneth the moſt appropriate effect of the Holy Ghoſt, which is the loue of God, <hi>which is ſhed abroad in our hearts by the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> without which loue, <hi>no man can</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 5. 1. Cor. 12. <hi>Tract.</hi> 74. <hi>ſuper Joh.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſay that Ieſus is the Lord; Nemo fic dicit, niſi qui diligit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:21376:12"/>
               <head>The Obiect of this Sinne; the Euangelicall Truth.</head>
               <p>THE holy Scriptures doe often vnder the name of <hi>truth,</hi> expreſſe vnto vs <hi>Chriſt;</hi> for he is <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Aquin.</hi> 2. 2. <hi>quaeſt.</hi> 1. <hi>art.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>veritas prima,</hi> ſay the <hi>Schoolemen,</hi> the <hi>firſt Truth,</hi> and the <hi>obiect</hi> of our <hi>faith;</hi> in as much, as he is the <hi>word of his Father,</hi> as he hath teſtified of himſelfe, and his Teſtimony is true; <hi>I am the Truth;</hi> and <note place="margin">Ioh. 14.</note> thus is he <hi>that Truth</hi> that maketh vs all true, for he teacheth vs all Truth.</p>
               <p>He is the moſt <hi>finall</hi> and <hi>formall obiect</hi> of our knowledge leading vs vnto knowledge, neither can any Truth be poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly knowne, but by the inſplendencie of this <hi>eternall Truth;</hi> whom the Spirit teſtifieth to be the Truth; The <hi>Truth,</hi> for that we haue all the promiſes of truth performed, and exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited in him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In his body a Communion, in his Blood the expiation of all our ſins, in his Soule, the price of our Redemption, in his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt. apud Albert. Ratiſp. Sup.</hi> 6. <hi>cap. Ioh.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>viuification, and a perfect reſtauration of our ſpirituall life, which was once loſt in his Deity and Godhead, the full perfection and complement of all grace;</hi> But for as much as this Truth is made manifeſt vnto vs, in the old and new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaments, Therefore the Scriptures are termed <hi>that Truth,</hi> becauſe Chriſt is reuealed vnto vs in them; and ſo our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſtileth them in his prayer to his Father; <hi>Sermotuus ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>eſt,</hi> thy word is thy Truth; And S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> diſtinctly ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth them that Truth that is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>according to</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Tit. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Godlineſſe,</hi> conſiſting in vnderſtanding the Law, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and beleeuing the Goſpell; for they expreſſe vnto vs that Truth whereby we muſt be ſaued.</p>
               <p>For what are the Scriptures? But Chriſt vayled; and what is Chriſt? but the vnmasking of the Scriptures:</p>
               <p>The word of Truth is the word of Chriſt, &amp; Chriſt is the Truth of this word.</p>
               <p>The Law led vs vnto him; the Patriarchs foreſaw him, the Prophets foretold him, the Euangeliſts writ the whole Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21376:12"/>
of his life; the Apoſtles preached the Goſpell of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The Goſpell (I ſay) that is (ſaith <hi>Chriſoſtome) the Ioyfull</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Praefat. a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uang Math.</note> 
                  <hi>meſſage of Saluation;</hi> wherein wee are certified, <hi>that puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is taken away, that Sinne is pardoned, that wee are San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, Iuſtified, Redeemed, Adopted to bee the Sonnes of GOD, made heyres of Heauen, yea wee who once were the Enemies of God, and ſate in darkneſſe, and in the ſhadow of Death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the effecting whereof the onely begotten Sonne of God, <hi>Veraciter factus eſt homo,</hi> was truely made man; In <note place="margin">Gregor.</note> the Sacrifice of our redemption, vouchſafed <hi>Mori vt vitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> to dye as a Calfe; By the power of his might, <hi>Surrexit vt Leo,</hi> did riſe againe like a Lyon, and aſcending vp into the Heauens; was <hi>Eleuatus vt Aquila,</hi> mounted like an Aeagle; where hee ſitteth in Maieſty and Glory, at the right hand of his Father, vntill he ſhall returne againe, at the fulnes of time to Iudge the world; and hath deliuered in the Interim to our cuſtody, his precions treaſure, which he will exact againe at our handes; Namely, the Law, and the Prophets, the Goſpell, the writings of his Apoſtles, his Sacraments, the grace of Remiſſion of Sinnes, and Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Dignity and Honour of his glorious Name, that wee are, and ſo likewiſe called Chriſtians; A people beloued of God, Elect and peculiar.</p>
               <p>Hee came into the world, to bee vnto the <hi>Iewes, a finiſher of the Law,</hi> and to the <hi>Gentiles, A Light in the middeſt of their darkneſſe,</hi> and <hi>a Rocke of Saluation to all that would</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>build on him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And though hee became vnto the vnhappy Iewes, <hi>Petra ſcandali, &amp; Lapis offenſionis,</hi> a Stone to ſtumble at, and a Rocke of offence; and to the Impious Gentile, <hi>In ſignum cui</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>contradicitur,</hi> for a Signe to bee ſpoken againſt; yet vnto vs who beleeue in him, hee is <hi>Power, Wiſedome, Righteouſnes,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.</note> and <hi>Redemption.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Out of the premiſes, I inferre this Concluſion; That
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21376:13"/>
whoſoeuer renounceth the word of God contained in the olde and new Teſtament, renounceth Chriſt alſo; for the word is the Law of God, which in the Old and New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, was deliuered by Chriſt; So that hee came into the world to the end to declare the Truth, which lay hid in the olde Law, and to beare witnes thereunto.</p>
               <p>And againe, ſuch a one maketh GOD the Father a Lyer, who in <hi>Iordan,</hi> and the Mount <hi>Tabor</hi> teſtified of CHRIST; <hi>This is my welbeloued Sonne, in whom I am well</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Math. 3. Mark. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>pleaſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For God as the <hi>Obiect,</hi> hath a double reference to our Faith; as the <hi>Medium,</hi> and <hi>Concluſion,</hi> the <hi>Forme,</hi> and the <hi>Matter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Sent. diſt.</hi> 23.</note> 
                  <hi>Id quo creditur, &amp; id quod creditur,</hi> ſaith <hi>Lumbard,</hi> As the <hi>End</hi> and the <hi>Meanes;</hi> hee is both the <hi>Agent,</hi> the <hi>Obiect,</hi> the <hi>End,</hi> and the <hi>Rule of our Faith,</hi> as hee is <hi>Veritas prima</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed by himſelfe in the Scriptures, becauſe the Scriptures, are the Miniſteriall reaſon of the Obiect of our Faith; for Faith is Ioyned to this <hi>Obiect,</hi> by this <hi>Medium;</hi> for the <hi>Scriptures</hi> are <hi>Deus dicens ſeipſum,</hi> ſaith <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Caietan ad</hi> 22. 2. <hi>Aquin. q.</hi> 2.</note> a Diuine, God declaring himſelfe to Mankinde.</p>
               <p>Therefore, whoſoeuer renounceth the Goſpell, renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth CHRIST alſo; And againe, whoſoeuer abandoneth that Truth of Chriſtian Religion, which is deriued thence, by neceſſary and Infallible conſequence, tearmed by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Chryſoſtome, Dogmatafidei,</hi> the principles and Articles of <note place="margin">Sup. verba. contextus.</note> Faith, forſaketh CHRIST IESVS himſelfe, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently relinquiſheth the whole meanes of Saluation, and muſt neceſſarily periſh.</p>
               <p>Hee that ſhall not in wordes confeſſe, and in deede main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, if need ſo require, to the ſtaking of his life thereon, the Honour of Chriſt his Sauiour; is worſe then an Infidell: for the Heathen themſelues affirme, nothing to be ſo Inhumane, ſo Beaſt-like, <hi>Quam committere, vt Beneficio victus eſſe videare;</hi> as to bee careleſſe to requite a good turne to the full; And if the Chriſtian ſhall bee ſilent in this, <hi>The very</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Math. 10.</note>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:21376:13"/>
                  <hi>Stones would cry out againſt him,</hi> If thou <hi>Deny him before Man, hee will deny thee before God;</hi> And better it is, that thou ſhouldeſt bee <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Chryſoſt. apud Hug. Sup.</hi> 10. <hi>Cap.</hi> Math.</note> 
                  <hi>Teſtis Chriſti,</hi> a witnes to maintaine the glory of thy Lord and Sauiour; then that thou ſhouldeſt hereafter finde CHRIST <hi>Teſtem contrate;</hi> a witnes to conuict thee of Infidelity.</p>
               <p>It is the higheſt degree of Ingratitude, to repay Euill for Good, and to ſcorne and diſgrace a Benefactor.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peremptoria res eſt Ingratitudo,</hi> ſaith <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ser.</hi> 5. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Bernard;</hi> Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude is a deadly thing, it ſlayeth the Soule, there is nothing ſo diſpleaſing to God, in the Children of Grace; and againe hee termeth it <note n="*" place="margin">Sup. Cant.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>entum vrentem,</hi> a burning winde, which dryeth vp the fountaine of Gods loue, the dewe of his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and floods of his Grace.</p>
               <p>Such like <hi>Methridates</hi> (who hated the Antidote which preſerued his life from the danger of poyſon) renounce the meanes, whereby their Soules are ſaued from <hi>Hell, Death,</hi> and <hi>Damnation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſuch are moſt like vnto mad Dogs, who runne chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with fury at their Maſters, from whome they receiued their breeding, and their feeding.</p>
               <p>And this is the true <hi>Sinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugning of Gods word, in manner aboueſaid, for that it proclaimeth the Majeſty, Wiſdome, and goodnes of God; and therefore hee that oppoſeth this Truth, oppoſeth Gods honour, the truth of Faith, which is the foundation of our Saluation.</p>
               <p>This is the <hi>Obiect</hi> of this Sinne; the Truth of Chriſtian Faith, which whoſoeuer Impugneth, is ſaid to <hi>reſiſt the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> by whom it is reuealed and infuſed into Man, and therefore hee is called <hi>Spiritus veritatis,</hi> becauſe hee lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth <note place="margin">Ioh. 16.</note> into all Truth.</p>
               <p>If any ſhould growe to that Impudence to deny Truth, in reſpect of the Entity thereof, hee is conuinced by the ſtrength thereof; for it beeing the light of the Soule, can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Set; for it caſteth her beames ſo ſtrongly on the Soule,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21376:14"/>
that a man cannot imagine it, not to bee; for if there bee no truth, it is true, that there is no truth, therefore ſomething is true; and if ſomething bee true, it is true, that there is Truth; therefore, if Truth be not, there is truth; See how the Truth pręuaileth <hi>aboue all thinges.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>iras.</note>
               </p>
               <p>God is the Fountaine of all Truth, and from him hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery truth his <hi>Emanation,</hi> and more eſpecially the Truth of Chriſtian Faith, which is the power of <hi>God vnto Saluation, vnto euery one that beleeueth,</hi> and that through the Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt;</hi> and conſequently hee Sinneth againſt the Holy Ghoſt, who doth hate, perſecute, or renounce the ſame.</p>
               <p>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> was once of Opinion, that <hi>No mans Conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience could hate GOD,</hi> but afterward he retracted it: at the firſt he did not remember the ſaying of the Holy Ghoſt; <hi>The preſumption of them that hate thee increaſeth euer more and more.</hi> For there are many that hate God; whom becauſe <note place="margin">Pſal. 74.</note> they know to bee an auenger of wickednes, they wiſh hee had no Beeing, for <hi>Qucm metui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> quiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> periricupit;</hi> and ſo though that all men by Nature deſire the knowledge of the Truth; yet <hi>ratione adiuncti</hi> or <hi>effectus conſequentis,</hi> he may abhorre it, and labour to doe pręiudice thereunto; So a man may hate God for his Iuſtice, which puniſheth Sinne, and his Truth which deſcryeth and reproueth the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Circumſtances, Beleefe in Chriſt, and knowledge of his Word going before, and yet Chriſt repudiated.</head>
               <p>NOw I come to the <hi>Circumſtances,</hi> without which wee cannot define this Sinne; for not euery one, that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth not the Goſpell in <hi>whole</hi> or <hi>part;</hi> is culpable of this great Sinne, yea though hee Impugne it, and therefore wee muſt diſtinguiſh.</p>
               <p>There are ſome, who as yet, haue not receiued the Faith; as <hi>Natiue Indian Idolaters,</hi> and other who neuer heard of it; <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Aquin.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">•</hi>. 2. <hi>quaeſt.</hi> 10. <hi>art.</hi> 1.</note>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:21376:14"/>
and theſe are termed <hi>Infidels, Negatiue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Or they haue once Beleeued, and after departed from it; and that either, <hi>a parte in aliquibus,</hi> in ſome particular <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tho. Elys.</hi> 19. <hi>in Clypeo piorum. queſt.</hi> 42. <hi>art.</hi> 1.</note> pointes by their vnderſtanding deceiued, and ſuch are ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Haretickes.</hi> Or <hi>a tota totaliter,</hi> from the whole in generall, by their Will and Affection depriued, and theſe are termed <hi>Apoſtatates.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt ſort, are not cenſured in my Text, becauſe they receiued it not; Nor the ſecond, becauſe they knew it not; But the third, are directly pointed at, who both receiued, and knew it.</p>
               <p>For the Cleering whereof, you muſt know, that as in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Obiects; there muſt bee firſt, a repreſentation of them to the Sences; Secondly, a Iudgement of the thinges repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by the Minde, for Iudgement is <hi>Completinum cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aquin.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">2</hi>.2. <hi>qu.</hi> 173.</note> the perfecting of knowledge.</p>
               <p>So before a man bee a perfect Chriſtian, two thinges are requiſite;</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Vt ſanè capiat ea quae Creduntur;</hi> that he verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aquin.</hi> 2. 2. <hi>qu.</hi> 9. <hi>art.</hi> 1.</note> the Articles of Faith.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Vt habeat rectum Iudicium de eis, diſcernendo credenda, a non credendis;</hi> that hee Iudge rightly and ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, what hee ought to beleeue, what to refuſe; both which are intimated in theſe wordes; Beleeued and knowne, as <hi>Anſelme</hi> and <hi>Bruno,</hi> expound them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The firſt Circumſtance; After wee haue receiued.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>To receiue the Truth,</hi> is to beleeue it, and to beleeue in <hi>Chriſt</hi> as the Truth teacheth vs; and thus the word is vſed by the <hi>Euangeliſt,</hi> where hee ſaith; <hi>That vnto as many as receiued Chriſt, hee gaue them power to be made the Sonnes</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>of God,</hi> and hee manifeſteth it in the wordes following, viz. <hi>To thoſe who beleeued in his Name;</hi> So <hi>Theophilact</hi> expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21376:15"/>
it; and in this Sence, Diuines expound this word of my Text; <hi>Anſelme,</hi> for <hi>inward Illumination; Bruno</hi> for <hi>Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the Goſpell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nature being blinde in Heauenly thinges, if it ſhould o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-rule in Man, muſt neceſſarily preuent his Saluation.</p>
               <p>For that the Naturall man Beleeueth nought, but that hee firſt apprehendeth by knowledge; when Diuinity, firſt doth require our confident aſſent to that it propoundeth, and after certifieth vs of the Truth by Euidence.</p>
               <p>Yea, wee haue an Inchoation of Bleſſednes in this life, by the aſſent of Faith, which compriſeth in her boundleſſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinet the end of our Hope; for in this, wee doe hope to bee bleſſed, becauſe wee ſhall ſee in <hi>open Viſion</hi> that Truth, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which wee doe now cleaue by <hi>Faith;</hi> for Faith maketh theſe thinges preſent in our heart, by the certainty of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe, and therefore is defined to bee <hi>A ſubſtance of thinges hoped for;</hi> as if it gaue a reall poſſeſſion of it to the Beleeuer. <note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Without which Beleefe, reaſon ſheweth, that Bleſſednes cannot bee attained; for though all men deſire it, yet who will vſe meanes, if he diſpaire to attaine; and therfore Hope is neceſſary; And againe, who will deſire to hope for that, he doth not Beleeue.</p>
               <p>And therefore it is neceſſary, firſt to beleeue in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and to beleeue thoſe thinges alſo, without which <hi>Chriſt</hi> cannot bee loued, that by beleeuing them, hee may ſhape his courſe toward him.</p>
               <p>Therefore CHRIST the Eternall word of his Father, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing according to his promiſe of olde; Aſſumed our Fleſh, ſuffered Death for our Sinnes, riſen vp againe for our Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, (which are incredible to the Naturall man, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God ſhould become Man, Dye as a man, and that man ſhould riſe from Death like God; and all this for Man) ought to bee entertained by Man, with great Ioy and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, becauſe by him wee are made the ſonnes of God.</p>
               <p>As hee hath performed theſe thinges for vs, ſo hee expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth that wee diſpiſe not this Grace, but earneſtly embrace
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21376:15"/>
it with thankeſgiuing, and build on him onely.</p>
               <p>For God (<note n="*" place="margin">Ser. de fide. Spe, et Char.</note> ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome)</hi> would haue Man proue toward him, as he hath ſhewed himſelf toward Man, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not attaiue vnto the reward, who will not profeſſe him; <hi>Nec accipere poteſt quod promittitur, niſi ante Impleuerit quod Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betur,</hi> nor can hee receiue the promiſe, who doth not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the condition, viz. <hi>Beleeueth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But hee that beleeueth not, <hi>is already Iudged;</hi> therefore <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.</note> our Sauiour ſaid, that the Holy Ghoſt <hi>would reproue the world of Sinne, becauſe they Beleeued not in him;</hi> and no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, <note place="margin">Ioh. 16.</note> becauſe <note n="*" place="margin">Auguſt. ibi.</note> 
                  <hi>Hoe manente, caetera dimittuntur,</hi> as long as incredulity remained, all other Sinnes abode, Originall and Actuall, but this being caſſeered, all were forgiuen; for faith in Chriſt, quitteth man of all, by apprehending the Merit of his paſſion, whoſe Blood ſhed, waſheth vs cleane from all our Sinnes.</p>
               <p>Hereupon, we renounce all things whatſoeuer, and our ſelues alſo, to follow him as his Seruants, Subiects, and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, and ſo to be reputed and termed; <note n="*" place="margin">Nazianz.</note> 
                  <hi>Inde Chriſtianus vocaris, quia in Chriſtum credis,</hi> Hence are we called Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, becauſe we beleeue in Chriſt;</p>
               <p>By which <hi>Name,</hi> we teſtifie, that we build onely on him, and acknowledge him for our King, and Redeemer, we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue all his Commaundements, and iudge his rule to be the perfection of life; Limiting our Beliefe to his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and we doe <hi>Huius iurare in verba Magiſtri,</hi> take an Oath of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leageance vnto him in Baptiſme, to confirme our fidelity; it being <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Baſi'. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cont. Eunom.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Sigillum fidei,</hi> the Seale of our faith; wherein we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the Croſſe on our forehead, which is the <hi>ſeate of ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtneſſe,</hi> in token, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. in Pſal.</hi> 130.</note> 
                  <hi>Ne Chriſti opprobrio Chriſtianus eru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſcat,</hi> that we ſhould neuer be aſhamed to confeſſe Chriſt crucified, and to fight vnder his Banner, vnto our liues end.</p>
               <p>Well then, art thou Baptized? art thou ſigned with the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Idem de Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clyſmate c.</hi> 9.</note> Kings Seale? beginneſt thou to feede at the Table of thy King? <note n="*" place="margin">Idem Epla. ad Arment. et Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin.</note> 
                  <hi>Noli eſſe Deſertor;</hi> become not a flincher; Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thy Couenant; * <hi>Quia iam vouiſti, iam te aſtrinxiſti;</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:21376:16"/>
the vowe hath bound thee; wretched art thou, if thou break thy vowe to God.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Heathen</hi> neuer forſake their Gods; but feare, reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and mainly defend them, leſt by changing their rights, they ſhould be taxed with <hi>error. Illi perſeuerant in falſo, ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> non perſeu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ras in vero?</hi> Shall they perſiſt in falſhood, and <note n="*" place="margin">Chryſoſt. ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil. de Ier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m. Prophet.</note> wilt not thou abide in the truth?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Socrates,</hi> though a <hi>Pagan,</hi> hauing denied ſacrifice to <hi>Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo,</hi> which was death among the <hi>Athenians,</hi> being aduiſed by <hi>Plato,</hi> to ſaue his life by flight, ſaid, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bonauent. in Luminar. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae, Serm.</hi> 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Abſit vt verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem negem, quam aſſerui,</hi> farre be it from me to denie that truth, which before I profeſſed; and therefore <hi>Plato</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing pondered with himſelfe the baſeneſſe of his Counſaile, was aſhamed thereof, and abſented himſelfe from his death.</p>
               <p>Who but a mad man would caſt away the Anchor of his ſhip in a tempeſt? who but a deſperate wretch would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect his pardon, being before condemned to death? or will any pitty him, who knowing himſelfe vnrecouerably ſicke; yet would caſt off that Phyſitian, who with his owne life hauing purchaſed a ſoueraigne Alexetery, proffereth him certaine recouery freely, if he will vſe it, and truſt vnto him, whereas otherwiſe, except he beleeue, he muſt dye, becauſe he deſpiſeth the ſole meanes of his preſeruation?</p>
               <p>Saint <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Homil.</hi> 25. <hi>in oper. Imperf. in Math.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> expreſſeth the ſtate of ſuch perſons, in a familiar ſimilitude. As the houſe (ſaith he) that hath a firme foundation; ſuffereth no great ruine, if part of the wall or roofe do fall, becauſe it may be repaired againe; but if the foundation fall, then the ruine is great; becauſe the whole tumbleth down: So if a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> commit fornication, adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, or manſlaughter, his fall is not great and vnrecouerable, becauſe hee may riſe againe by repentance, as <hi>Dauid</hi> did; But if the foundation of his faith faile, that he turne Pagan, and become vnbeleeuer, then his ruine is great and vnreco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerable, for the whole periſheth.</p>
               <p>And ſuch ſinne more heinouſly, then thoſe, who neuer
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21376:16"/>
knew him, or beleeued in him; and <hi>Chriſt</hi> is more offended at them.</p>
               <p>Truly ſpake the * Poet; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <note place="margin">Sophocles.</note>
               </p>
               <p>There can be no greater ſore, then a falſe friend, whom a man can neither <hi>fugere, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fugare;</hi> ſhunne nor baniſh; So <hi>Chriſt</hi> complaineth, that if <hi>an enemie had diſhonourea him, he</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bern.</hi> Pſalm. 55.</note> 
                  <hi>could haue bare it; but his companion and familiar friend to betray him, made it execrable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He was grieued at the <hi>Infidels</hi> vnder the <hi>Law of Nature;</hi> but more at the <hi>Iewes,</hi> vnder the <hi>Law of Moſes,</hi> becauſe his loue was greater vnto them:</p>
               <p>But moſt againſt <hi>Iudas</hi> vnder the <hi>Law of Grace</hi> for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying him; it appeareth by the diuerſity of their puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;</p>
               <p>The firſt he drowned, which was an eaſie death: The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <note place="margin">Gen. 7. Num. 15.</note> he ſtoned, which was a more greeuous death.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Iudas</hi> the Traytor hung himſelfe, which was a moſt ſhamefull death, and accurſed; and the rather becauſe hee <note place="margin">Math. 27.</note> was of the number of thoſe, to whom he had ſaid, yee are my <note place="margin">Ioh. 15.</note> friends.</p>
               <p>We doe worthily deteſt <hi>Cains</hi> iniquity, <hi>Lamech</hi> his cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, <hi>Chams ſubſannation, Iſmaelsferity, Eſaw</hi> his pertina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, <hi>Abſalon</hi> his malice, the peruerſity of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, But all theſe are nothing to that incomparable villany of <hi>Iudas,</hi> in betraying his Lord and Maſter, whom he belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to be the ſonne of the euer-liuing God, and the Sauiour of mankind; this impiety was aboue all other; of an <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> who ſhould haue bin one of the 12. Iudges ſitting in glory to iudge the 12. Tribes of Iſraell, to become a Traytor againſt him who called him to this high dignity; and therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his monſtrous ingratitude, the diuell entred into his heart, and carried him headlong to the acting of his Treaſon, and from thence deſpairing of pardon, to hang himſelfe, where he braſt aſunder; and his bowels guſhed out; Surely <hi>Iudas</hi> committed that Sinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt; for ſo great was his malice againſt <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that if it had beene poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21376:17"/>
he would haue had not his fleſh onely, but his ſoule, and Diuinity alſo to be deſtroyed; hee betrayed him to death, whom he beleeued to be the Lord of life: yet ſuch was his moſt indurate malice, that nothing could withhold him from his purpoſe; though <hi>Chriſt</hi> vſed many meanes and admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions vnto him;</p>
               <p>Loue, in waſhing his feete; <note place="margin">Ioh. 13.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Feare,</hi> when he ſaid, woe vnto him, by whom the Sonne <note place="margin">Luc. 22.</note> of man is betrayed.</p>
               <p>Sorrow, when he foretold his betraying. <note place="margin">Ioh. 13. Math. 26.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Shame, when he ſaid vnto <hi>Iudas,</hi> Thou haſt ſaid.</p>
               <p>Yea ſo great, that he ſeemed after a ſort to doe wrong vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Iuſtice, in vſing ſo great mercy toward him; yet hee would not be ſaued, and becauſe he would not, he was dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, (yea if a man may ſo ſpeake) againſt Chriſts will.</p>
               <p>Their Sinne (who hauing once giuen their names vnto Chriſt, entertained the truth of his Goſpell, and reſolued their conſciences thereof, yet ſhall after fall away from the ſame) is like vnto that which <hi>Iudas</hi> the Traytor committed; for ſuch Crucifie to themſelues againe the Sonne of God, and make a mocke of him, and are ſaid to deſpite the Spirit of Grace; which is the true ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt. By faith we are made the ſonnes of God, which faith is wrought in our hearts, by the Holy Ghoſt, and is called in this reſpect the <hi>Spirit of Adoption, whereby we crie Abba Father: bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>witneſſe with our Spirit, that we are the Children of God;</hi> by this Spirit <hi>wee are ſealed vnto the day of Redemption;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.</note> Some Tranſlations haue it <hi>in the day of Redemption:</hi> the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers expound it <hi>in the day of Baptiſme,</hi> and the reading and expoſition is good; for the Holy Ghoſt ſealeth vs in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme by faith, and maketh vs to be <hi>de Regio grego,</hi> nor ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth <note place="margin">Théophylact.</note> vs to ſtand among the guilty and damned, and hath ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated vs to <hi>Redemption. Noli ergo Signaculum illud diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluere;</hi> If thou fall away from thy faith, thou doeſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite the Holy Ghoſt who did worke this in thee; thou had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt receiued a Benefit, and reiecteſt it after; thou deſpiſeſt
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21376:17"/>
the giuer; he made thee the Sonne of God, thou wilt be the Seruant of the Diuell; he came to ſaue thy Soule, and thou doeſt thruſt him out of dores, and ſeeke to bring him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion; thou doeſt herein reſiſt plainely, and perſecute the Holy Ghoſt; and like <hi>Iudas</hi> art a Traytor vnto him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Second Circumſtance.</head>
               <p>IT ſufficeth not a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> to haue <hi>Faith,</hi> to <hi>Beleeue,</hi> but hee muſt haue <hi>Vnderſtanding</hi> and <hi>Knowledge,</hi> ioyned to his Faith, to Iudge rightly of the Articles of Religion; which Faith otherwiſe cannot doe, becauſe it hath but vnperfectly participated of the Diuine light.</p>
               <p>For though there bee an Irradiation from the Eternall Truth; yet is it not <hi>Plenary;</hi> becauſe as yet, <hi>Manet Specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum &amp; aeuigma,</hi> the vayle is not remoued. <note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore in this darkenes, wee muſt ioyne the other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, which God hath aſſigned, viz. the <hi>Vnderſtanding,</hi> which though it bee, but as a Candle (compared to Faith) ioyned to the <hi>Sunne;</hi> yet it is certaine, that a man ſeeth bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by the light of a Candle, then of the Sunne, if the ſame be ecclipſed.</p>
               <p>Therefore, what <hi>Faith</hi> entertaineth, the <hi>Vnderſtanding</hi> admireth, examineth, and often diſcouereth and maketh knowne; For there are ſome things, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lumbard. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Sent. diſt.</hi> 24.</note> 
                  <hi>Que creduntur, &amp; nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam Intelliguntur,</hi> which are Beleeued, but neuer vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood; As the Myſtery of the Trinity, and the Incarnation, and ſuch like; and thoſe, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Aquin.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">•</hi>. 2. <hi>quaeſt.</hi> 8. <hi>art.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Directè cadunt ſub fide,</hi> are appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by Faith onely, but the vnderſtanding cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize them, and therefore admireth them.</p>
               <p>And there are other, * <hi>Quae prius creduntur, &amp; poſtea In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telliguntur;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Lbmb. vbi ſap.</note> which are firſt beleeued, and after vnderſtood; as are ſome principles of Faith, gotten by hearing, reading and meditation; And theſe belong vnto Faith, <note n="*" place="margin">Aquin. vbi ſup.</note> 
                  <hi>Vt ordinata ad fidem,</hi> as Inſtruments to build Faith in man; as the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of holy Scripture.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:21376:18"/>
Of the firſt, wee cannot haue, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bonauen. Sap.</hi> 3. <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nt. diſt.</hi> 24.</note> 
                  <hi>Cognitionem a parte com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prahenſionis,</hi> a totall and perfect knowledge, while wee are heere in <hi>Via, Pilgrims,</hi> as God ſhall be knowne by vs here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, <hi>In Patria,</hi> in our heauenly Manſion.</p>
               <p>But of the Second in many pointes, wee may haue ſuch knowledge heere, yea the firſt, may <hi>Imperfectè intelligi,</hi> in part bee vnderſtood, and that <note n="*" place="margin">Aquin. vbi ſupra.</note> 
                  <hi>Intellectu Negatiuo,</hi> as farre forth, as the vnderſtanding findeth no Obſtacle to impaire <note n="*" place="margin">Caictan in Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ad cundum lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note> the verity of them; yea both may bee beleeued, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in ſome ſort, <hi>Manu ductione ratiocinationis</hi> by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſtigation <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bonauent. vbi ſu ra.</hi> Rom. 1.</note> of Naturall reaſon, as the Heathen Phyloſophers thus knew God.</p>
               <p>And an antient Diuine ſaith; that to make the Faith mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rich. de Scto. vict. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de Trinit. cap.</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Non tantum poſſunt heberirationes probabiles, ſed eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am neceſſariae,</hi> wee may finde both probable, and neceſſary reaſons alſo, though ſometime wee cannot eſpy them.</p>
               <p>Thus theſe holy Fathers, aſſembled in the Councell of <hi>Nice,</hi> did by Naturall reaſons ſeeke to demonſtrate vnto <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cyzicen. in com. Act. Conc. Nic. pt.</hi> 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Phaedo</hi> and other Phyloſophers, whome <hi>Arr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us</hi> had condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted thither to defend his Blaſphemy, the whole Myſterie of the <hi>Trinity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For ſuppoſe, one beleeuing one GOD, and the ſame to bee the vniuerſall Creator, ſhould after by neceſſary reaſons begin to know the fame, hee ſhould become neuer the more faithleſſe; and therefore the <hi>Schoole man</hi> ſaith well, that howſoeuer, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Aquin.</hi> 2.2. <hi>qu.</hi> 2. <hi>art.</hi> 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Rationes praecedentis fidem,</hi> doe <hi>Minueremeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum fidei,</hi> yet <hi>Subſequentes augent;</hi> Not to beleeue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reaſons, doth impaire the worth of Faith; yet to Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the Faith, after wee haue already Beleeued with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, dignifieth the ſame; for it maketh a man more firmely and with greater delight, to cleane vnto the Truth, and to teach and conuict other.</p>
               <p>But wee vſe Reaſon onely, * <hi>Admanifeſtationem fidei,</hi> to <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Idem pt.</hi> 12. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>art.</hi> 8. <hi>Bonauent ſuper</hi> 3. <hi>Sent. diſt.</hi> 25. <hi>queſt. vlt.</hi>
                  </note> make the Faith knowne, that thereby it may receiue a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter growth; * <hi>Non a parte veritatis dictantis,</hi> not in reſpect of the Diuine Truth it ſelfe, but in reſpect <hi>Intellectus aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientis,</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:21376:18"/>
of the weakenes of our vnderſtanding, which is beſt led by the Senſes.</p>
               <p>Therefore the Schoole-men ſay, that <hi>Knowledge</hi> is more <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Idem. ibid. diſt.</hi> 23. <hi>queſt.</hi> 4.</note> certaine then <hi>Faith,</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>certainty</hi> of <hi>Speculation,</hi> becauſe a man may know a thing ſo certainly by knowledge that hee can by no meanes doubt of it, diſclaime it as falſe, or any way contradict it in his heart, as it appeareth in the knowledge of <hi>firſt principles;</hi> though <hi>Faith</hi> bee more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine in regard of the <hi>firmity of Adhaeſion,</hi> for Faith will maintaine, what knowledge cannot conceiue.</p>
               <p>And in this ſenſe <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 14. <hi>de Tr. n. Cap.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> expounding theſe wordes of the Apoſtle; <hi>To another, is giuen the word of knowledge;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.</note> aſcribeth to this knowledge, the <hi>Generation, Nutrition, maintenance,</hi> and <hi>ſtrengthning of Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And for this cauſe, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hugo de Scto. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de ſacram pt.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Hugo</hi> rightly placed theſe two diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences in the Definition of Faith; <hi>viz.</hi> that it is, <hi>A certainty of the Soule,</hi> placed <hi>Supraopinionem, &amp; infra Scientiam,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue Opinion, and beneath Knowledge; Becauſe the one is but a bare <hi>eſtimation. Cum formidine oppoſiti,</hi> alway vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine of the Truth; Now <hi>Faith,</hi> is a doubtles <hi>approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Aquin.</note> 
                  <hi>by way of aſſertion.</hi> But the acceſſe of knowledge, giueth a <hi>Reall poſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſion</hi> of the <hi>Truth;</hi> So that it is more profitable to man, in reſpect of attaining and retaining the perfection of Truth; as it is more ſecure, <hi>to ſtand by Faith,</hi> then <hi>to wauer by Opinion,</hi> and to ſee a thing preſent, then to beleeue it ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
               <p>Yea the <hi>Habite</hi> of Faith, cannot fully bee had without <hi>knowledge,</hi> for the <hi>vnderſtanding</hi> muſt bee inſtructed in the Articles of Faith, before it can conſider them.</p>
               <p>This is the <hi>Materiall part of</hi> Faith, <hi>Id quod creditur,</hi> (ſaith <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Sent. diſt.</hi> 23.</note> 
                  <hi>Lumbard)</hi> the Articles of our Beleefe; and in this reſpect, Faith is rightly ſaid to be <hi>Acquiſita,</hi> or <hi>ſuaſa,</hi> gotten by out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward meanes, becauſe no man knoweth how many, or what <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hales pt.</hi> 1. <hi>queſt</hi> 1. <hi>Memb.</hi> 10.</note> Articles of the Faith there are, vntill hee hath learned them by reading or hearing, let him gape as long as hee pleaſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Anabaptiſticall reuelations: and thus the Apoſtle ſaith, <note place="margin">Rom. 10.</note>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:21376:19"/>
                  <hi>Fides ex audito,</hi> Faith commeth by hearing.</p>
               <p>And this Knowledge, is earneſtly to bee ſought after; leaſt it vnhappily fall out, <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Origen. lib.</hi> 8, <hi>in Epiſt. ad Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo cap.</hi> 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Vt in fide poſiti, fruſtremur a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de,</hi> that wee hauing once beleeued, ſhould fall away from the Faith; for they who are careles to vnderſtand by know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, the truth of that they Beleeue, they doe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> beleeue in vaine, and may <hi>Euaneſcere in fide,</hi> fall from the <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1. <hi>Orig. ibid.</hi>
                  </note> Faith.</p>
               <p>Hereupon the Apoſtles deſired our Sauior, to <hi>Encreaſe their Faith,</hi> by imparting knowledge vnto them; for this <note place="margin">Luk. 17.</note> knowledge maketh vs to feele (as it were) with the Hand of Experience, the Truth, and therefore maketh vs more confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to build on it, and more firmely to adhaere vnto it.</p>
               <p>Therfore to make the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> more conſtantly to perſiſt <note place="margin">Deut. 6.</note> in his Seruice, God commaunded them, <hi>To ſeeke after the knowledge and vnderſtanding of the Law, hee commandeth them to learne it themſelues, to teach it to their Children, hee enioyneth Meditation thereof in all places, and at alltimes, at home, and abroad, lying downe, and riſing vp, he commandeth to make them the Obiect of their Sences, to binde them for a ſigne on their hands, and as frontlets betweene their eyes, to write them on the poaſtes of their Houſes, and on their Gates;</hi> For thoſe things which wee haue learned and taught others, and doe continually thinke of, and which are the day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obiect of our Sences; as thoſe thinges wee haue in our hand, of our feeling, and the thinges wee doe beholde with our eyes, of our Sight; or thoſe places vnto which wee haue frequent recourſe, as the doores of our Houſe, cannot bee forgotten by vs.</p>
               <p>Therefore in another place hee ſaith more manifeſtly; <hi>Forget not the thinges, which thine eyes haue ſeene, that they</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 4,</note> 
                  <hi>depart not from thine heart,</hi> as if hee ſhould haue ſaide; The Euidence of knowledge ſhould ſo perſwade the heart, that it ſhould neuer bee moued from it's reſolution; So that hee, who once hath receiued the Faith of CHRIST, and after by ſearching the Scriptures, findeth certaine teſtimony of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21376:19"/>
the power, and efficacy thereof vnto Saluation to euery <hi>One that Beleeueth,</hi> hauing his <hi>Vnderſtanding quit from Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, his Iudgement from Error, his Conſcience, and Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>alſo perſwaded of the truth hereof,</hi> and bearing witnes thereunto; what remaineth? but that ſuch a one (if hee not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the pręcedence) renounce the Faith, and perſecute it, <hi>ſpreta Conſcientia,</hi> in deſpite of his Conſcience, is an <hi>Aduerſary to the Holy Ghost,</hi> becauſe hee reſiſteth his Grace; viz. <hi>The Illumination of his Soule by Faith, the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>of the Heauenly Guift, of remiſſion of Sinnes by Hope, the partaking of the Holy Ghoſt, in his Guiftes, by knowledge and vnderſtanding, the taſting of the good word of God, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward delectation conceiued by hearing the Goſpell preached; and the taſting alſo of the powers of the world to come, as life euerlaſting, by hope.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A fearfull fall, and incredible to ſome, that a man ſhould riſe to that <hi>height,</hi> and fall ſo farre away again, &amp; that againſt his knowledge and Conſcience.</p>
               <p>Impoſſible, it is not; for <hi>Sinne</hi> diſordereth the <hi>Affection,</hi> not the <hi>Vnderſtanding;</hi> The <hi>Holy Ghoſt enlightneth euery</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>man that commeth into the world;</hi> as well the wicked as the Godly, the <hi>Reprobate</hi> as the <hi>Elect;</hi> reuealing vnto the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate; not perſwading their Conſciences, enlightning their vnderſtanding, not ſanctifying their Affection; like the Sunne, which with her Beames, onely enlightneth the Moone, but heateth the Earth moreouer vnto fertility.</p>
               <p>The Reprobate haue him, <hi>Secundum infuſionem,</hi> for a time infuſed into them, after which, hee departeth from them; for <note n="*" place="margin">Rich. de Sanct. vict. Ser. deſper. Sancto.</note> 
                  <hi>vadit, et venit; recedit et redit;</hi> Hee goeth, and commeth, departeth, and returneth;</p>
               <p>The wicked taſt him, but reliſh not the ſweetnes, becauſe of their diſtempered pallat, or foule ſtomack, which maketh them belch vp the ſweetneſſe againe, and therefore it doth not nouriſh them, though for a while it may delight them.</p>
               <p>Therefore ſuch are but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Temporarie Beleeuers;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Math. 13. 1 Ioh. 2.</note> neither were they <hi>of Chriſt; for had they beene of Chriſt, they</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:21376:20"/>
                  <hi>had continued with Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hom.</hi> 35. <hi>in Math. Sup. haec verba, Tranſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s blaſ he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mabant cum et Anſelm. Ibid.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Origen</hi> ſaith, It is <hi>Opus praeter euntium,</hi> the property of vnſtable perſons onely, to blaſpheme Ieſus; No conſtant man blaſphemeth Ieſus; for their feete are placed on a Rocke; But if they fall, or paſſe by him, they blaſpheme him, and thoſe who nod the head at him, hauing no firme head; but ſuch in Minde and Affection are moueable to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith, it is <hi>Summa Delicti, non agnoſcere quod ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Tract. de Idol. van.</note> 
                  <hi>are non poſſis;</hi> The extremity of Sinne, not to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that, whereof thou canſt not be ignorant;</p>
               <p>In what State is he then, who denieth, what he beleeueth, and knoweth to be that Truth, by which he muſt be ſaued, and of Enuie moreouer diſgracefully reuileth it, and cruelly perſecuteth it?</p>
               <p>Such are <hi>perfect Blaſphemers;</hi> and therefore <hi>Caietane</hi> rightly iudged, <hi>Blaſphemos non eſſe Infidoles;</hi> that Infidels <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ad quaest.</hi> 13. 2.2. <hi>art.</hi> 1.</note> could not commit this <hi>Blaſphemie</hi> againſt the Holy Ghoſt; becauſe Blaſphemers know they Sinne in this kinde againſt their Conſcience, and are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, condemned by the verdict thereof; But the <hi>intention</hi> perfecteth it in the Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, <note place="margin">Tit. 3.</note> and their Sinne is more grieuous; <hi>for it had beene better</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Pet. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>for them, neuer to haue knowne the way of righteouſneſſe, then after they haue acknowledged it, to turne from the Holy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement giuen vnto them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therfore our Sauiour conuicteth the <hi>Phariſies</hi> of this Sinne; becauſe they both heard him, ſaw him, &amp; by his ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar words and workes, like vnto which, neuer man vttered or acted before; knew him to be the Sonne of God, and yet they <note place="margin">Ioh. 15.</note> hated him; and perſecuted him euen vnto death.</p>
               <p>Whereby they manifeſtly declared themſelues to be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of that great Sinne, maliciouſly controling the operation of the Holy Ghoſt in their ſoules, who could not be ignorant who Chriſt was, and whence he came.</p>
               <p>What that Sinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt ſhould be; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Ages, haue produced diuers opinions.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:21376:20"/>
S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <note n="*" place="margin">Exampla. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ad. Marcell.</note> 
                  <hi>Hierom</hi> ſaid, it was, <hi>Cum videas in virtutibus Deum, Belzebub calumniari in factis;</hi> to aſcribe Gods manifeſt power to the Diuell.</p>
               <p>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sup. cap.</hi> 12. <hi>Luc.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Ambroſe, to denie Chriſts Diuinity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <note n="*" place="margin">Ser. de vurbis domini.</note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaid, it was finall <hi>impenitence;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>St.</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 12. <hi>Sup. Math.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Hillary; Diuin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> virtutis poteſtatem negare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To denie the power of Gods might.</p>
               <p>Some ſay; it is to <hi>thinke amiſſe of the Holy Ghoſt, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his Eſſence or Equality.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Schoolemen</hi> for the moſt part; <hi>Abijcere per contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Super.</hi> 2. <hi>Sent. diſt.</hi> 43. <hi>et Summuſtae Sup.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Aquin. q.</hi> 14.</note> 
                  <hi>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> per quaehomo retrahitur a peccando;</hi> to reiect with diſdaine, thoſe meanes, by which a man is with-held from ſinning; And they make ſixe kindes hereof; <hi>viz.</hi> 1. <hi>Deſpaire;</hi> 2. <hi>Praeſumption;</hi> 3. <hi>Enuie of his Brothers Grace;</hi> 4. <hi>Impug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the knowne Truth;</hi> 5. <hi>Obſtinacie, and finall Impaeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some haue ſaid, it is <hi>Infidelity; other; Sinne againſt a mans conſcience;</hi> and ſundry other opinions, there haue bin, which I purpoſely omit.</p>
               <p>Being then compaſſed about with ſo great a cloud of wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes; what remaineth, but that <hi>wee looke to</hi> IESVS, <hi>the Author and finiſher of our Faith?</hi> and ſeeing the Myſterie of <note place="margin">Heb. 12.</note> this queſtion is great, let vs with <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> ſeeke for light, to expound it from the Lord.</p>
               <p>Our Sauiour CHRIST, hauing by his Diuine power cured one who was blinde and Dumbe, and caſt out the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill <note place="margin">Math. 12.</note> where with hee was poſſeſſed, was by the <hi>Phuriſes</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiouſly accuſed, to haue caſt it out by the power of <hi>Belze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bub,</hi> the Prince of the Deuils; Whereupon our Sauiour ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing conuicted them, ſheweth their dangerous eſtate, and dreadfull Sinne; which hee termeth <hi>Sinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> which conſiſted herein, that they <hi>Blaſphemed the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and Blaſpemy importeth the intended deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ones good Name.</p>
               <p>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Mathew,</hi> giueth ſome light hereunto, and ſaith it is to <hi>ſpeake againſt the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> And S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Marke</hi> ſpecifieth it,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21376:21"/>
for they ſaid; <hi>Hee hath an vncleane Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that they did attribute to the Deuill thoſe Actions, <note place="margin">Mark. 3.</note> which they knewe to bee proper vnto God, as the Eiection of Deuils.</p>
               <p>Neither did they this <hi>Ignorantly,</hi> for <hi>Intelligentes Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum, principem daemoniorum eſſe dicebant;</hi> though they knew him to bee the Sonne of GOD, yet they termed him <note place="margin">Ierom.</note> 
                  <hi>Belzebub;</hi> and our Sauiour ſaid, They knew him &amp; <hi>whence hee was;</hi> Yea graunt they had beene deceiued by the vayle <note place="margin">Joh. 7.</note> of his Fleſh, yet could they not haue beene Ignorant, that the caſting out of Deuils, was the proper worke of God.</p>
               <p>But they did it of <hi>Malice,</hi> for though they knew him to bee <hi>the Heyre, yet they conſpired to ſlay him,</hi> And thus, they termed him a <hi>Samaritane,</hi> notwithſtanding they heard him <note place="margin">Math. 22.</note> Diſpute of the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> and the <hi>Iudgement</hi> to come; <note place="margin">Ioh. 8.</note> both which, the Samaritans deny.</p>
               <p>So that they did (euen againſt their knowledge and conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience) impugne the grace of God, and kingdome of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who came to the end, hee might diſſolue the workes of the Deuill; and they beheld his effectuall performance thereof, in many his Miracles, all tending to the Glory of God, to the good of Man, and to the downfall of <hi>Sathan,</hi> the Spirit alſo teſtifying to their Spirit, that it was the power of God; all which notwithſtanding they blaſphemed CHRIST.</p>
               <p>Out of the premiſes; I deduce this Definition of Sinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> is: <hi>a to all Apoſtacy from Chriſt and his Goſpell; A reiecting, reſiſting, ſuppreſſing, blaſpheming and perſecuting in thought, in word, in Act; cauſleſly, wilfully, malitiouſly, of the true Chriſtian Religion: the which religion; the party before embraced, and profeſſed, and in which Chriſt hee verily beleeued and did farther know by plaine and infallible Euidence, the ſame Chriſt and his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, to be the whole, true, and ſole meanes of Saluation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The which Sinne, is termed by our Sauiour, <hi>Blaſphemie againſt the Holy Ghost,</hi> whether by the Holy Ghoſt, as by
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21376:21"/>
an <hi>eſſentiall Name,</hi> hee would deſigne vnto vs the whole <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Antoxin. part.</hi> 2. <hi>tit.</hi> 8. <hi>Cap.</hi> 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Trinity;</hi> euery perſon whereof is a <hi>Spirit</hi> and is <hi>Holy;</hi> and hee who offendeth one, offendeth euery one; or elſe, (which I take to bee more proper) the Third perſon in the <hi>Trinity,</hi> by his <hi>perſonall Name,</hi> one of whoſe <hi>Attributes is; to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 16. Ioh. 1. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 5.</note> 
                  <hi>with the Truth, and to teſtifie to the Truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that I conclude this point; <hi>That as no man can ſay, that Ieſus is the Lord, but onely by the Holy Ghoſt; So no</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>man ſpeaking by the Holy Ghoſt, can ſay that Ieſus is exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable;</hi> But ſuch a one reſiſteth the Holy Ghoſt, and <hi>ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>a word againſt him, becauſe the Spirit teſtifieth to his Spirit, that Ieſus is the Lord, and ſuch make the Holy Ghoſt a Lyar;</hi> which is Blaſphemie in the higheſt degree. <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Sequel or effect of this Sinne,</hi> viz. <hi>Deſtitution of remedy;</hi> In theſe wordes; <hi>There remaineth no more Sacrifice for Sinne.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe whole Goſpell is a Song, either of Ioy and Melody, or of Sorrow and Lamentation; deliuering either the glad tydings of Saluation, to inuite vs to ſeeke after it; or the heauy Doome of euerlaſting Damnation, to deterre and affright vs from Sinne and Impiety.</p>
               <p>In theſe wordes, thoſe who haue receiued the true Faith of Chriſt, and know likewiſe, Saluation to conſiſt therein, and yet wilfully renounce it, and maliciouſly perſecute it, are preſented with their fearefull eſtate, which is, to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute, and depriued of that Benefit, which Chriſt imparted to all conſtant Beleeuers, <hi>viz.</hi> to bee a ſacrifice for their ſinnes.</p>
               <p>Wee know that <hi>Sacrifices</hi> in the olde <hi>Law</hi> were ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, one for to bee a <hi>Propitiatory ſacrifice</hi> for the ſinnes of the people, to pacifie the wrath of God againſt thoſe ſinnes, and to waſh them cleane from their Iniquity.</p>
               <p>The other, conſiſted in a kinde of <hi>Latreia,</hi> or forme of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21376:22"/>
Seruice done vnto God, not that they in themſelues, were effectuall to reconcile man vnto Gods grace and fauour, and to blot out his Sinne, but that they might typically reſemble that <hi>true Sacrifice,</hi> which was after fully offered by Chriſt on the Altar of the Croſſe.</p>
               <p>In which one Oblation, and moſt perfect Sacrifice, wee haue perfectly, whatſoeuer the law of <hi>Nature</hi> or <hi>Moſes</hi> did either figure, or vnperfectly repreſent.</p>
               <p>For by this, our Sinnes are blotted out; for <hi>hee was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered for our Sinnes;</hi> By this wee receiue that grace where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> we are ſaued; <hi>For Chriſt being conſecrate, was made the Author of Eternall Saluation for all that did obey him;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 5.</note> By this wee obtaine the perfection of glory, for <hi>by the Blood of Ieſus, wee may bee bolde to enter into the holy place.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 10.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Oh (ſaith a deuout man) God hath giuen vs a liuely, pure <note place="margin">Gerſ. Sup. Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſicat.</note> Sacrifice full of goodnes, full of thoſe effects, for which the Legall Sacrifice was wont to bee offered vp; wilt thou haue thy ſinnes blotted out? <hi>Behold the Lambe of God which ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>away the Sinnes of the world;</hi> wilt thou giue thankes vnto God? <hi>Chriſt gaue it vnto his Father:</hi> wilt thou auoyd euill? <hi>Hee healeth thee and ſetteth thee free,</hi> for <hi>he tooke our Infirmities on himſelfe:</hi> wilt thou obtaine a ſpeedy <note place="margin">Eſay. 53.</note> good at his hand? <hi>Aske the Theefe,</hi> and hee will tell thee, <hi>What Chriſt promiſed,</hi> and confirmed vnto him, in his Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Sacrifice; <hi>Verily I ſay vnto thee, this day ſhalt thou bee</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Luc. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>with me in Paradice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Leuiticall Law, hee was reſembled by a <hi>Galfe,</hi> a <hi>Ramme,</hi> a <hi>Goate,</hi> a <hi>Lambe,</hi> which were to bee offered; <hi>But neither the blood of Bulls and Goates, nor the aſhes of an Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, nor the Fleſh of Lambes and Goates, could pacific the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>wrath of GOD againſt Sinne; for hee tooke no pleaſure there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; But the Blood of Chriſt, which through the eternall Spirit, offered himſelfe without fault to God, to purge our Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from dead workes, and hath obtained Eternall redemption for vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>Lambe</hi> hee was called becauſe of his <hi>Innocence;</hi> a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21376:22"/>
                  <hi>Ramme,</hi> becauſe of his power; a <hi>Goate</hi> becauſe of his like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes <note n="*" place="margin">Appearing in the ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of ſinfull Fleſh.</note> to <hi>Sinne;</hi> a <hi>Calfe</hi> becauſe of the <hi>vertue of his Croſſe.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gloſ. ord. in</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> Leuit.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Yea, all theſe ſignified the Fleſh of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which was a moſt perfect Sacrifice, and that in foure reſpects.</p>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe the Fleſh of mans Nature was fit to bee offered for Man, who had offended.</p>
               <p>Secondly, becauſe it was paſſible and Mortall, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was fit for Immolation.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, becauſe it was without Sinne.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, becauſe it was the Fleſh of him that offered it; it was therefore acceptable vnto God, becauſe of his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable Charity, that offred his owne Fleſh.</p>
               <p>Which <hi>Auguſtine</hi> obſerued; <hi>Quid tam Congruentur ab</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de Tri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. Cap.</hi> 14.</note> 
                  <hi>hominibus Sumeretur, quod pro eis offeretur, quam humana caro?</hi> What could be taken ſo fitly by Men, to bee offered vp for men, as the Fleſh of Man? and what was ſo fit for Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice as Mortall fleſh? and what ſo cleane to purifie the Sinnes of mortall Men, as Fleſh voyde of the contagion of carnall concupiſcence, borne of the wombe of a Virgine? and what could bee ſo thankefully offred and accepted, as the fleſh of our Sacrifice, being made the Fleſh of our Prieſt.</p>
               <p>Hee was that Prieſt, by whome wee are reconciled; hee was that Temple, in which wee are reconciled; hee was that God vnto whom wee are reconciled.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Behold the man, who hath giuen himſelfe, an Offering, and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>a Sacrifice of a ſweete ſmelling ſauour vnto God for vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is that Sacrifice for Sinne, with which God is pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; God will not bee pacified without <hi>Chriſt,</hi> for without the <hi>ſhedding of Blood, there is no Remiſſion.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 9.</note>
               </p>
               <p>By this meanes the Soule wrapped in Sinne, muſt appeare before God, firmely beleeuing that his Sinnes are purged by the Blood of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in the multitude of the mercies of God, as hee himſelfe hath ſaid; <hi>Though your Sinnes were as red as</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eſay. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Scarlet, I will waſh them as white as Snow.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All the waters of <hi>Iordan</hi> cannot cleanſe our Leproſie, but
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21376:23"/>
the Blood of IESVS onely, hath that abſterſiue facultie to purifie our Soules of the foyles of Sinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Chryſoſt. hom.</hi> 13. <hi>in Cap.</hi> 7. <hi>ad Heb.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Non eſt aliud Sacrificium,</hi> there is no other Sacrifice, this One hath purged vs, if this fayle <hi>Ignis &amp; Gehenna;</hi> Hell fire followeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nullius Martyris ſanguis,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine;</hi> The blood of no Martyr was ſhed to this end.</p>
               <p>Miſerable therefore is their caſe, who truſt to the <hi>Supere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation</hi> of their <hi>Saintes,</hi> in their paſſions, exceeding their owne Sinnes; whereas they are taught by their own School-man, that the merites of the Saintes, were <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Dom. Soto. ſup.</hi> 4. <hi>Sent. diſt.</hi> 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Vltra condignum remunerata a Deo, &amp; exhauſta,</hi> rewarded aboue their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert by God, and exhauſt on themſelues.</p>
               <p>But wee are Sanctified, euen by the <hi>Offering of the Body of Ieſus Chriſt once made, and with this one Offering hath</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>hee Conſecrated for euer, them that are ſanctified.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Behold the vertue of Chriſt his Sacrifice; <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Haymo. in cap.</hi> 7. <hi>ad Heb.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Vnum enim fuit, &amp; ſemel oblatum, &amp; ſufficit in ſempiternum, ad tollenda omnia peccata Credentium;</hi> This one Sacrifice, once offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſufficed for euer, to take away all the Sinnes of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, ſeeing that <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſych. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Sup. Leuit.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Perfectio &amp; omnimoda noſtra ſalus, &amp;c.</hi> That the Sonne of God by Sacrificing himſelfe hath fully accompliſhed our ſaluation, and that there can be no ſatisfaction for Sinne, <hi>Niſi in vertute paſſionis Chriſti,</hi> but onely in the vertue of Chriſt his Paſſion; It remaineth, that whoſoeuer renounceth the ſame, reiecteth the ſole meanes of his Saluation, and muſt conſequently periſh euerlaſtingly.</p>
               <p>This is that <hi>chiefe Corner ſtone, Elect and precious,</hi> In <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note> which, whoſoeuer Beleeueth ſhall not bee confounded; But vnto the Diſobedient, hee is a Stone whereat they ſtumble, and ſtumbling fall, and falling looſe their liues, and winne Death, and purchaſe to themſelues damnation.</p>
               <p>Whoſoeuer therefore cleaueth vnto Chriſt, with a firme Affection is quit from all Sinne, and fully reconciled vnto God; but whoſoeuer deſpiſeth him finally, periſheth euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21376:23"/>
for the <hi>Wrath of God abideth vpon him for euer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hence it appeareth, that wilfull and malicious <hi>Apoſtacy,</hi> from Chriſt and his Goſpell, before profeſſed Zealouſly and according to knowledge; is that Sinne againſt the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> which our Sauiour ſaith, ſhall neuer bee forgiuen, and the reaſon of the Irremiſſibility thereof is made manifeſt, viz. <hi>Adeſertion,</hi> and malitious Impugning of the onely meanes of Remiſſion, the Sacrifice of our Redemption, <hi>Christ Ieſus our Sauiour,</hi> and his Goſpell.</p>
               <p>And heere is the error of the <hi>No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atians</hi> made apparant, who Interpreted this Scripture, of thoſe who through feare of Death, or paines of torture, denyed or Blaſphemed Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How, or whither Sinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt is Irremiſsible.</head>
               <p>BVt let vs without pręſumption more curiouſly exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine this point; which hitherto by any Diuine which I haue read, hath not beene exactly diſcuſſed, nor certainly determined; that it may bee ſaid of thoſe, who haue entred vpon it; <hi>Quot capita, tot ſententiae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Retract. Cap.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, wee may not deſpaire, of ſuch a one while hee liueth.</p>
               <p>Of the ſame opinion is S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.* <hi>Ambroſe.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sup. cap.</hi> 3. <hi>ad Gal.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>St.* <hi>Hierome,</hi> ſeemeth to holde it Irremiſſible, for hee ſaith; That if <hi>Peter</hi> had committed this Sinne, hee had not <note place="margin">Epiſt. de trina. negat. Petri.</note> beene forgiuen.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Hillarie</hi> ſaith, that CHRIST denyeth <hi>Blaſphemiae</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 17. <hi>Sup.</hi> Math.</note> 
                  <hi>ſpiritus Iudulgentiam,</hi> pardon to the Blaſphemy of the Spirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hugo de Sancto victore,</hi> ſaith; that <hi>No</hi> man can giue a <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> 55. <hi>Sup. piſt. ad Rom.</hi>
                  </note> certaine Definition of this Sinne, yet this is knowne, <hi>Quod ſi quis ſic peccarit, num quam conſequetur veniam,</hi> that if any man commit it; hee ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eder be pardoned.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:21376:24"/>
And expounding the 4. 5. and 6. Verſes, of the ſixt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> hee ſaith; It ſeemeth to vs that in this place, and in the Tenth Chapter of this Epiſtle, the Author deſcribeth the Sinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt; <hi>In cuius barathbrum quioun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>, ſemel inciderit Impoſſible eſt quod paenitentiam conſequatur aut Salutem;</hi> Into the Gulfe whereof, whoſoeuer once falleth, it is impoſſible, that hee ſhould euer attaine Repentance or Saluation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Richardus de Sancto victore,</hi> ſaith; That if ſome bee <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Tract. de Spir. Blaſphem.</note> 
                  <hi>guilty of a Temporall Sinne,</hi> in regard of Gods Iuſtice, wee may beleeue, that other may bee <hi>Temporally guilty of an Eternall Sinne,</hi> in regard of his Mercy.</p>
               <p>The <hi>School-men,</hi> for the moſt part ſay; <hi>Vix raro, difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sup.</hi> 2. <hi>Sent. diſt.</hi> 43. <hi>&amp; Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſtae Sup. Aquin.</hi> 2. 2. <hi>queſt.</hi> 14. <hi>Ientac.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>remittitur,</hi> it is ſcarce, ſeldome, hardly forgiuen, neuer read to haue beene forgiuen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Caeietan</hi> ſaith, that God hath denyed to ſuch remiſſion and repentance, and to ſpeake regularly; it is neuer forgiuen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Almayne</hi> ſaith, it may bee forgiuen, becauſe a man may repent of it before his Death. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Moral. cap.</hi> 28.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>Armachanus</hi> ſaith, It is one of thoſe heynous Sinnes, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 9. <hi>de queſt. Armen. cap.</hi> 27.</note> for which a Man cannot obtaine pardon, though hee ſhould repent neuer ſo heartily.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the Opinions of Men incomparably Learned and Iudicious in their time, vnto whom wee aſcribe due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, and glorifie God for his Graces beſtowed on them to the Illumination of his Church.</p>
               <p>But foraſmuch as theſe forenamed worthyes, neuer deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that their Authority, Antiquity, or Learning, ſhould praeiudice verity, as it appeareth by their owne Confeſſions, (for that were; to ſtop vp the way which leadeth to finde the Truth) I am bolde therefore to trauaile after them, in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition of this Myſterie, and aſſuming by the way, what they had found and diſcouered before, I will annex ther eun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, what I ſhall Iudge to the farther Illuſtration of the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity, ſo farre as God hath enabled mee, ſubmitting the whole to the Cenſure of the <hi>Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:21376:24"/>
A Sinne, may be ſaid to bee <hi>Irremiſſible,</hi> for one, or all of theſe reſpects following.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Either Abſolutely in its owne Nature:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Or in reſpect of the <hi>Actiue Power of the forgiuer:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Or in reſpect of the <hi>Preparitine diſpoſition of the offender.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In reſpect of the Sinne it ſelfe; it hath this common vnto it, with all other Sinnes; that it meriteth Eternall Death, but it hath this <hi>proper</hi> vnto it ſelfe, that it is <hi>Irremediably mortall, perpetually puniſhed,</hi> and <hi>Neceſſarily Irremiſſible;</hi> and therefore it is termed by St. <hi>Iohn, Peccatum ad mortem, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſiue,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5. <hi>Caiet. vbi Sup.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>for which hee would not haue vs to pray.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For as in Bodily death, there are three thinges:</p>
               <p>Firſt, loſſe of Life.</p>
               <p>Secondly, corruption of Diſpoſition of the Body to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue Life.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Impoſſibility of reperation by Nature.</p>
               <p>So in this Sinne, there are three Circumſtances which make the Offender vnrecouerable.</p>
               <p>Firſt, loſſe of the Soules life, by Apoſtacy; <hi>For euery Branch that abideth not in Chriſt withereth, and is caſt into</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.</note> 
                  <hi>the Fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, a generall De-ordination or deprauation of the powers, and faculties of the Soule, by malice and hatred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God; which <hi>rebuketh the holy Spirit of Diſcipline,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sap.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>when it commeth, that Grace cannot enter into their wicked heart.</hi> For as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith; <hi>Aduer ſus gratiam, qua re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliatus</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de Ser. Dom. in Monte.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>eſt Deo, inuidioe facibus agitatur,</hi> they rage with Enuy, againſt that Grace, whereby they ſhould bee reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto God.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, an Impoſſibility of reſtitution by Repentance; <hi>For their Heart is waxed fat, and their Eares are dull of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eſay. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>hearing, and with their Eyes they winke; leaſt they ſhould ſee with their Eyes, and heart with their Eares, or ſhould vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand with their Heart, and ſhould returne, that God might heale them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that they had rather <hi>ſe nunquamſaluari, quam Chriſtum</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Anſel. Sup.</hi> 9. <hi>Cap. Math.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:21376:25"/>
                  <hi>recipere,</hi> bee eternally damned, then receiue CHRIST; So that the Sinne is <hi>Impugnatiuum Medici &amp; Remedij,</hi> Impug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Compend. Theol. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 29.</note> the Phyſitian and his Medicine, <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Sacrifice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, a Sinne may bee ſaid to be Irremiſſible; in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the power of the forgiuer; There is no Sinne ſo great and deadly, which God cannot forgiue, in reſpect of his power which is <hi>Abſolute;</hi> but this Sinne hee cannot for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue, in reſpect of his power which is <hi>Ordinate;</hi> becauſe <hi>Deus nihil poteſt contraſe</hi> God can doe nothing againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Anſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lm. Proſo. log. cap.</hi> 7. 2. Tim. 2.</note> or his Truth. For the Apoſtle ſaith; <hi>Hee cannot deny himſelfe;</hi> vpon which wordes, <hi>Anſelme</hi> alledgeth, <hi>Dioniſias</hi> thus fitly reaſoning to my purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Suimet negatio, caſus veritatis eſt, veritas autem</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>eſt, &amp; veritatis caſus, non</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Dioniſ. Areopag.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The denyall of himſelfe, is the fall of the Truth; but the Truth is <hi>Exiſtent,</hi> or <hi>being,</hi> and the fall of the Truth is <hi>Non</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, not Being; If therefore the Truth be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is <hi>Exiſtent,</hi> and the denyall of the Truth <hi>Non</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, not <hi>Exiſtent;</hi> the fall of Exiſtent, is to fall from Beeing; for God cannot fall, and not be <hi>Non</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, not <hi>Exiſtent;</hi> And therfore he cannot forgiue this Sinne, without the <hi>Annihilation</hi> of himſelfe, and his Kingdome.</p>
               <p>And therefore <hi>Zanchius</hi> note is obſeruable, ſaying; This <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sup.</hi> 1. <hi>mandat.</hi>
                  </note> Sinne, doth <hi>Ingulum Dei petere,</hi> intend the Ruine, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of God.</p>
               <p>And becauſe there is no other <hi>Saluation</hi> then by the Death of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> therefore alſo is this ſinne Irremiſſible.</p>
               <p>Becauſe Chriſt Death (in the opinion of a worthy Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine) <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Raymund. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band. in viola animae Dia'og.</hi> 6 <hi>Cap.</hi> 61.</note> which was conſummated with ſuch wicked handes, cannot blot out that Sinne, by which it is wrought; His rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is annexed, <hi>Cum ipſa circa hunc plus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>peratur mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> quam mors eius operetur Bonum.</hi> Seeing the ſlaying of Chriſt, was farre more heynous, then the ſauing of Man by Chriſt his Death, was precious; for Chriſt his Death reſpecteth vs onely, who are <hi>nothing;</hi> but their <hi>ſinne</hi> tendeth vnto him, who is <hi>Infinite in Goodnes and Maieſty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:21376:25"/>
And this opinion, with the Reaſon of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Anſelme. Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam peccatum quod contra perſonam illius fit, Incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biliter</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Cur Deus homo. cap.</hi> 14.</note> 
                  <hi>ſuperat omnia alia, que extra perſonam illius cogitari poſſunt;</hi> Becauſe that Sin, which is committed againſt <hi>Chriſt</hi> his perſon, doth incomparably exceede all thoſe, which may be conceited without his perſon.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, a Sinne may be irremiſſible, in reſpect of the <hi>praeparatiue Diſpoſition of the offender.</hi> It is a true Saying of <hi>Auguſtine; Qui creauit te ſine te, non iuſtificabit te ſine</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">De verb. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini.</note> 
                  <hi>te,</hi> Hee that made thee without thy helpe, will not iuſtifie thee without thy conſent; for vnleaſt thou turne to God by Repentance, God will not turne to thee by forgiueneſſe; for before Repentance, man is not Suſceptible of Gods Grace, by which Remiſſion of Sinnes is wrought; But ſo foule is this Sinne (as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith) <hi>vt deprecandi humilitatem</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de Ser. dominim Monte</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ſubire non poſſit;</hi> That the Offender cannot humble him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to craue pardon, but they rather lift vp their Horne againſt the Lord, and his Annointed, and they haue <hi>propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum non paenitendi,</hi> a reſolute purpoſe neuer to repent; Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bona. in</hi> 2. <hi>Sent. diſt.</hi> 43.</note> could they repent, it were poſſible, which they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doe, <hi>Quod ſcilicet aeterna caecitate, &amp;c.</hi> Becauſe they are <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Caluin. Inſtit. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</note> ſtrucken with vnrecouerable blindnes for their Ingratitude, and at their beſt, they proue but like <hi>Iudas, Quem non pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentia</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> poenit. diſt.</hi> 3. <hi>cap. Sceleratior. ex Leone.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>duxit ad Dominum, ſed Deſperatio traxit ad La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queum;</hi> whom repentance drew not backe to the Lord, but Deſpaire to the Halter; who ſorrowed not, <hi>propter amorem Dei,</hi> for the loue he bare to God whom hee betrayed; but <hi>propter enormitatem rei,</hi> for the haynous treaſon he commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and <hi>Ibi nulla Reniiſſio, vbi nulla poſſit eſſe poenitentia,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gorrhan. Pet. Mart. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>loc.</hi>
                  </note> there can be no pardon, where there can be no Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
               <p>To be briefe (as the Apoſtle ſaith) <hi>It is impoſſible, that</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. Heb. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>they who were once lightned, and haue taſted of the heauenly gift, and were made partakers of the Holy Ghoſt, and haue taſted of the good word of God, and of the powers of the world to come, If they fall away, ſhould be renewed againe by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:21376:26"/>
                  <hi>ſeeing they crucifie againe to themſelues the Sonne of God, and make a mocke of him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Vpon which words <hi>Anſelme</hi> writing ſaith; that therefore it is impoſſible, that ſuch ſhould be renewed; <hi>Quia nolunt renouari,</hi> becauſe they will not be renewed; So that, <hi>Non eſt excuſatio Infirmitatis eorum, ſed culpa voluntatis,</hi> They cannot excuſe themſelues by pleading Infirmity, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the peruerſeneſſe of their owne will, who had rather abide as they are, then be renewed;</p>
               <p>For ſo execrable an hatred doe they carrie againſt God, which (as the Apoſtle ſaith of Charity) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Neuer falleth away;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore one rightly expreſſed the Nature of this Sinne, <note place="margin">Ex vet. quodam Ma. ſcrip. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Sup. Math. ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nymo.</note> that it is, <hi>Sibi ipſi cauſa, et ſemper cauſa eſt, et ſemper eſt;</hi> It is cauſed by the party himſelfe, and this cauſe is perpetuall, and the Sinne which is the effect, is perpetuall alſo; So that their Malice continueth againſt God, euen in death; and they that depart out of this life, with hatred toward God, <hi>Sub</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ich. de Sancto vict. tract. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pi, Blaſphem.</note> 
                  <hi>eodem morbo in aeternum tabeſcunt,</hi> Euerlaſtingly lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh vnder the ſame diſeaſe; and euer hating, neuer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and therefore hee termeth this Sinne, <hi>Aeternum Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum,</hi> the euerlaſting Sinne; and neuer repenting; hee is <hi>aternaliter reus eternidelicti,</hi> for euer culpable of the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Sinne.</p>
               <p>Hereupon the Ancients made <hi>finall perſeuering therein,</hi> to be <hi>complementum huius peccati,</hi> the Conſummation of this Sinne; which is true if it be ſpoken, by way of <hi>Neceſſarie</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hugo Card. Sup.</hi> 12. <hi>cap. Luc.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Concomitance</hi> not of <hi>caſuall euent;</hi> for then euery ſinne wherein a man departeth out of this life <hi>Impaericent,</hi> were <hi>ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiſſible,</hi> which is falſe; Therefore in my Text, wee finde <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in the praeter Imperfectence, praeſuppoſing a continuall progreſſe therein, as the Greeke Scholiaſt hath <note place="margin">Occumen in Enarrat. ad hunc locum.</note> obſerued before me.</p>
               <p>Therefore <hi>Auguſtine</hi> iudged this ſinne to be vnpardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, <hi>Non quia Blaſphemia, ſed quia ex Maleuolentia,</hi> not <note place="margin">Lib. quaeſt. de viro<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> teſt. mixt.</note> as it is ſimple Blaſphemy; But becauſe it proceedeth from,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:21376:26"/>
and is alway accompanied with Malice againſt God, which neuer ceaſeth.</p>
               <p>So that this ſinne, may be ſaid to be vnpardonable, <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Compend. Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>ca.</hi> 29</note> as the Diuels which neuer ſhall be forgiuen;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Preuatiue,</hi> becauſe there is no Congruence in this Sinne to be forgiuen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Contrary</hi> becauſe it hath a Diſpoſition reſiſting remiſſion.</p>
               <p>I will adde the Iudgement of <hi>Scotus</hi> for a Summary.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ad peccatum in Spiritum Sanctum, requiruntur tria;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sup.</hi> 2. <hi>Sent. diſt.</hi> 43,</note> Three things muſt concurre, to the conſtitution of that Sin againſt the Holy Ghoſt;</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>ſet Malice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>it muſt be againſt the Commaundements of the firſt Table,</hi> (which reſpecteth the whole duty of Man vnto God.)</p>
               <p>Thirdly, it muſt be attended with that, which moſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth Conuerſion vnto God, which is <hi>finall Impenitence;</hi> not becauſe a man dieth without Repentance, but becauſe he hath a purpoſe neuer to repent, which proceedeth of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire, <note place="margin">Lih. de ſide ad Petrum.</note> as it doth appeare ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in <hi>Cayn,</hi> and <hi>Iudas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And let this ſuffice, to haue beene ſpoken of this fearefull ſinne, according to the capacity of my ſhallow vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: If any one thinke otherwiſe, I refuſe not his opinion, if it may appeare true.</p>
               <p>Let euery one, who wiſhcth well vnto his owne ſoule, looke into himſelfe; that there be not found in him, an <hi>euill and vnfaithfull heart, to depart away from the liuing Lord.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Let euery one proue himſelfe, <hi>Whither he be in the faith, examine himſelfe, know himſelfe, whither Ieſus be in him, or</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>that he be a Reprobate; for if any one withdraw himſelfe, my</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>ſoule ſhall haue no pleaſure in him, ſaith the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God forbid, that either <hi>Atheiſme</hi> ſhould ſo blinde vs, or <hi>Mahumetiſme</hi> alienate vs, or <hi>Iudiaſme</hi> ſuſpend vs, or <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrifie</hi> poyſon vs; or <hi>Papiſme</hi> delude vs; or <hi>Epicuriſme</hi> corrupt vs; that we ſhould either with <hi>Diagoras, Deum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludere</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:21376:27"/>
ſtatly denie God; or with <hi>Protagoras, Deum in d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium vocare,</hi> once doubt whither there be a God or no. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>actant.</hi> 1. <hi>de falſ. rei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>g. cap.</hi> 2.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Or that with <hi>Mahumedes Sergius,</hi> and the <hi>Turkes,</hi> wee ſhould denie Ieſus to be God, and affirme him to be the Son of <hi>Mary, Et non niſi nuncium Dei,</hi> and but onely an Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour of Gods, as other Prophets before him had been; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Alchoran. Azea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 12.</note> and that Chriſtians erre, making him their God, <hi>Pluſquam praedicauerit nobis,</hi> more then he commanded or required at our hands, and that therefore we reape no benefit by him.</p>
               <p>Or that with the <hi>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gabond Iewes,</hi> wee ſhould renounce him, becauſe hee brought not the whole world at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, vnder his ſubiection, and gathered not their out-caſts from all parts of the world together, built them not a new Ieruſalem, in <hi>Mount Syan,</hi> and gathered them not thither, to obſerue the whole Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> in great peace, and proſperity, and made them not immortall, and impaſſible therein; and that therefore wee ſhould expect another <hi>Meſſias.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Or that with the <hi>ſuperſtitious Papiſts,</hi> wee ſhould by faigning falſe things of Chriſt, not worſhip him but our owne fictions, and aſcribe the honour proper vnto him, to other, which is <hi>omnino non colore,</hi> not to worſhip him at all. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>act. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>b.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 19.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Or that with the <hi>voluptuous Epicure,</hi> we ſhould neglect his ſeruice, and liue to our ſelues onely; as if hee regarded not, what Man doth on Earth, nor reſpecteth the Honour man ſhould giue him.</p>
               <p>Or that with the <hi>painted Hipocrite;</hi> wee ſhould be Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians but in ſhew, like ſome of the Courtiers of <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Chlorus,</hi> who choſe rather to renounce Chriſt, then the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Puſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>b. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de vit. conſt. cap.</hi> 11.</note> Emperours Seruice, whom he afterward worthily reiected; <hi>as Traytors to him who would not be faithfull to God;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Or but to ſerue their owne turne, like the greedy Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers of <hi>Conſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ntine the great,</hi> who were Chriſtians <hi>opinione</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Idem lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de vit. Conſtant. cap.</hi> 54.</note> 
                  <hi>tantum,</hi> in conceit onely.</p>
               <p>And therefore ready to turne with euery blaſt of winde,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21376:27"/>
like <hi>Ecebolius the Sophiſt of Conſtantinople,</hi> who conformed <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Socrat. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt. Eccleſ. cap.</hi> 11.</note> himſelfe to the diuers Religions of ſundry Emperours.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Conſtantius Iuntor</hi> ruled, hee ſeemed a zealous Chriſtian: when the Empire came vnto <hi>Iulian the Apoſtata,</hi> he as earneſtly maintained <hi>Paganiſme,</hi> and when <hi>Iouianus</hi> was Emperour, he embraced Chriſtianity againe; and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting himſelfe on his face, before the Church gate, cryed out, <hi>Me quaſi Salem inſipidum pedibus conculcate,</hi> tread mee like vnfauourie Salt vnder your feete.</p>
               <p>Into any of theſe may the Naturall man fall, through In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity of the fleſh, or ignorance in the vnderſtanding; But that a Chriſtian, who hath once taſted of the ſweet Mercies of the Lord, embraced the Goſpell, certified his conſcience thereof, and reioyced therein, ſhould notwithſtanding, after deſpiſe it, reiect it, perſecute it, in heart, in word, in act, not through infirmity, nor by ignorance, but of meere malice againſt God, to cenſure ſuch as I am not able; <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>incit offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um linguae, ſceleris magnitudo.</hi> It is a Sinne vnſpeakeable.</p>
               <p>For ſeeing it is true of Chriſt; <hi>Pro omnibus quae tribuiſti</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Chryſoſt. apud Bonau. lib. de grad. virt.</note> 
                  <hi>nobis O Chriſte, nihil aliud petis quam ſaluari, hoc ipſum tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buens, et acci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ientibus gratias agens;</hi> for all the good things that thou haſt giuen vs O Chriſt, thou craueſt at our hands, no other reward, then that we would vouchſafe to be ſaued by thee, both giuing vs Saluation, and thanking vs alſo, that we will receiue it.</p>
               <p>Is not he then deſeruedly permitted to ſlaughter his owne ſoule, who is cruell to himſelfe, yea Enemie to loue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, becauſe he would haue vs ſaued?</p>
               <p>The conſideration whereof moued <hi>Policarpus,</hi> that holy <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> when he was exhorted and commaunded to blaſpheme <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to diſdaine his owne life, and to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere the <hi>Proconſull</hi> in theſe tormes; <hi>Foureſcore and ſixe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſeb. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ccleſ. hiſt. cap.</hi> 15.</note> 
                  <hi>yeares haue I ſerued him and hitherto hath he hurt me in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing;</hi> and how can I then, <hi>Maledicere Regime<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> qui me ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uabit.</hi> Blaſpheme my King who ſaued me?</p>
               <p>We liue in a colde age, wherein the Soules of men are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nummed,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:21376:28"/>
hauing no ſparke of Deuotion, vnſtable, and Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, as ready to fall downe to <hi>Baall,</hi> as to the true God of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> yea to forſake CHRIST, and to worſhip <hi>Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How lightly doe men eſteeme the Sinne of <hi>Apoſtacy</hi> from the Goſpell, it appeareth by the multitude of thoſe, who dayly paſſe away from vs to Popery, and thoſe not onely of the baſe and Ignorant ſort, who like the <hi>Iew</hi> in the <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> paſſe from one Sect, to another, <hi>Vt multas corradant pecuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Socrat. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>Eccl. hiſt.</hi> 17.</note> In hope of gaine to enrich themſelues thereby? But of the Learned, and thoſe who know the Law of God; yea the Sonnes of <hi>Leui</hi> betray the Temple, they who ſhould preſent other vnto <hi>Chriſt,</hi> flye themſelues from Chriſt, and rayle at the <hi>Holy one of Iſraell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if their malice againſt Man, make them take Armes againſt GOD, their ſtate is damnable, like <hi>Tertullian,</hi> who at the firſt, ouerthrew the Blaſpemies of <hi>Heretickes</hi> by his writings, <hi>Velut quibuſdam fulminibus,</hi> as it were with ſo many thunderbolts, yet in the end, to auenge himſelfe of the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ncent. Lyr. cont. haer. cap.</hi> 24</note> Roman Clergie, hee fell away from the Truth, to <hi>Monta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ambitious Spirits, impatient of the aduancement of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons more worthy then themſelues, perfidiouſly flye to the Tents of <hi>Antechriſt,</hi> where they may open their mouthes vnto <hi>Blaſphemy againſt God, to Blaſpheme his Name, and</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Apocalips 13.</note> 
                  <hi>his Tabernacle, and them that dwell in Heauen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thinke you it a ſmall matter, to make a mocke of the Goſpell, by Cauponizing the Scriptures, to palliat your <hi>Cauterized</hi> Conſciences; like <hi>Arrius</hi> that wretch, who broached his peſtilent Blaſphemy againſt <hi>Chriſt,</hi> of meere malice, becauſe that good <hi>Alexander</hi> was worthily elected <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Theodor. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>hiſt.</hi> Eccl. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</note> Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria</hi> before him?</p>
               <p>The Church is happily deliuered of ſuch Monſters; and though ſhee be <hi>Pia &amp; Miſericors Mater,</hi> glad to receiue her loſt Children louingly, yet ſuch proue for the moſt part vnnaturall, and diſpiſe her; and returne not with a minde to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:21376:28"/>
perſiſt; like <hi>Ecebolius</hi> whom the Church had twice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, but as hee was light and vnconſtant at the firſt; <hi>Sic quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> poſtea permanſit,</hi> ſo hee continued to the end, ſaith the <note place="margin">Socrat. vbi ſupra de codem.</note> Hiſtory.</p>
               <p>I ſay not, that ſuch commit that <hi>Sinne against the Holy Ghost;</hi> but this <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith; <hi>Hee that is not with mee, is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me.</hi> And this I ſay; Hee that flyeth to the Tents of <note place="margin">Math. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Antechriſt</hi> and ſpeaketh and writeth matters, againſt the ſuggeſtion of his owne Conſcience, tending to the diſhonour of Chriſt, and his Goſpell; perſecuting that Truth in other, which they profeſſe ſecretly in themſelues, ſuch cannot be free from this Sinnc; yea this Sinne in them is <hi>Inchoatum</hi> begun, they being <hi>Haeretici ſcientes,</hi> witting Heretickes, and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>kam. Dialog, lib.</hi> 4. <hi>part.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 3.</note> are no better then their reprobate Father <hi>Balaam,</hi> who louing the reward of <hi>Iniquity,</hi> gaue councell, how the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Iſraell</hi> might bee drawne no offend God, forgetting what hee Propheſied before, and what hee had heard from <note place="margin">Num. 22.</note> God, accounting all for nothing, that hee might ſatisfie his owne couetous minde.</p>
               <p>Wherefore ſhould not the <hi>Apoſtates</hi> in this Age, receiue the like Cenſure, which the Church in her firſt, and ſecond <hi>Primatiue,</hi> and all other eſtates, inflicted vpon baſe reuol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and that with ſtrict Seuerity? That is, that <hi>No Clergy</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Diſt. So. cap. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>los ex Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtino.</note> 
                  <hi>man of what eſtate ſoeuer, hauing once fled away to the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſary, and returned againe to the Church, Ad Clericatum redeat, vel in Clero permaneat,</hi> Should execute that holy Function, or not rather be degraded from the ſame.</p>
               <p>This was S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> his cenſure, for meaner crimes, prouoked by the zeale of Gods houſe, to this rigorous Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline; But when preſently after, hee cenſureth weightier offences, vnder an Indefinite terme; wherein hee includeth, <hi>A temporary Apoſtacy of an ambitious minde, intending a ſeeming panitentiall returne, to the end, hee might bee congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulated by the Church with high preferment,</hi> (as it appeareth by his wordes) He peremptorily ſaith; <hi>Hoc ſacri Canones irrecuperabiliter deijoiunt;</hi> Such are degraded without any
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:21376:29"/>
hope of reſtauration to their Prieſtly Function; So that he ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerely determined, <hi>Vt poſt actam paenitentiam de damnabili crimine, nemo ſit Clericus,</hi> Notwithſtanding their Pennance ſuch was their crime, that they might not regaine the vſe of their Prieſthood.</p>
               <p>This Cenſure, was ſtoutly executed againſt <hi>Arrius</hi> by <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Socrat. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Eccl. hiſt. Cap.</hi> 20.</note> that inuincible Champion of Chriſt his Church, renowned <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> that vndanted Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the menacing Letters of the Emperours, directed vnto him in the behalfe of <hi>Arrius,</hi> for his reſtauration into the Church; vnto whom hee would in no wiſe condiſcend; Signifying vnto <hi>Conſtantine</hi> likewiſe by Letters, that it could not bee; <hi>Vt illi qui fidem irritam feciſſent, quibuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ab Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia Anathema eſſet denunciatum, tanquam poſt liminio re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuntes, gradum ſuum recuperarent;</hi> That they, who had once renounced their Faith, and receiued an Anathema from the Church, ſhould receiue their Degree againe in the Church, returning home againe as perfidious <hi>Fugitiues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor was this ſeuerity newly then practiſed in the Church; for <hi>Cyprian</hi> himſelfe that glorious Martyr, whoſe ſinguler lenity appeareth, in his Impugning the auſterity of the <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatians,</hi> (who would admit none into the Church who was once fallen in perſecution, though through infirmity) wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thus of the Admiſſion of reuolters, after the penitentiall reuerſion: <hi>Satis eſt talibus reuertentibus veniam dari, non tamen debet in domo fidei perfidia permanere.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 2. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ph.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Let it ſuffice thoſe Apoſtates, that at their returne, they receiue pardon of their offence; nor let them expect, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy their former office of Prieſthood in the Church, becauſe of their perfidious Excurſion; For what ſhall wee reſerue for the Good, Innocent, and thoſe who haue conſtantly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in the Church, if we honour thoſe, who haue gone out from vs, and rebelled againſt the Church?</p>
               <p>Of <hi>Trophinus</hi> the Prieſt, who fled but onely to the <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations,</hi> (who were rather Schiſmaticks then Heretickes) this is his cenſure.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:21376:29"/>
After Conference (ſaith hee) with other Biſhops held, <hi>Trophimus</hi> was receiued, but the rather, becauſe many Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 2. <hi>ad Anton.</hi>
                  </note> who were gone out from vs, returned againe with him; yet ſo was hee admitted, <hi>Vt Laycus communicet,</hi> to conuerſe in the Church as a Layman, <hi>Non quaſi lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um &amp; Sacerdotis vſurpet,</hi> and not to execute the Office of a Prieſt; yet would hee not aſſent that they ſhould bee ſo receiued, <hi>Ante Exomologeſim publicam, ante peractam publice paeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam cum ſatisfactione, ante manum ab Epiſcopo, &amp; vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſo</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>clero in paenitentiam lapſis impoſitam;</hi> Before publicke confeſſion made, before publicke pennance done with ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, before the Biſhop and Clergy had laide their handes on them, to receiue them as penitents; Hee moſt eagerly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buketh it, and moſt exactly prohibiteth, the Euchariſt to be adminiſtred vnto ſuch, or offered vp for them.</p>
               <p>Of ſuch, ſaith <hi>Conſtantinus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> in the <note place="margin">1 <hi>queſt.</hi> 7. <hi>cap. conu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus.</hi>
                  </note> Councell of <hi>Melda; Si quis ſponte ad Haeriticos vadit, &amp; accipit ordinationem, non recipiatur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If any one, who before was an Orthodoxall Chriſtian, goe out vnto Hereticks, and receiueth Orders at their hands, let him not vpon his penitentiall returne home againe, bee receiued into the Church as a Prieſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tharaſius</hi> the Patriarch accordeth in the next place; and the holy Synode concludeth, <hi>Hoc eſt iuſtum iudicium,</hi> this is iuſt Iudgement. Certaine it is, that Clergy and Laity, were lyable in auncient times to a fourefold puniſhment, viz. <note place="margin">Archidiac. ex. Goff. in Sum. de haeret. punit.</note> 
                  <hi>To Excommunication, to Depoſition from Orders or other Dignity, Confiſcation of their goods,</hi> and laſtly <hi>to milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Perſecution,</hi> and to bee deliuered ouer, to the <hi>Secular power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No leſſe, or greater Seuerity, was extended againſt Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, by the ancient Decrees of Chriſtian Emperors; They <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cod. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>tit.</hi> 10 <hi>Si quis lege</hi> 3. <hi>Hi qui Sanctam</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>confiſcated their Goods, they were depriued of the ordinary ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill Priuiledges of Chriſtians, they might not ſucceed in Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, or bee made heyres of the Goods or Lands of their Parents, they were baniſhed into moſt remote Territories;</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:21376:30"/>
                  <hi>they were neuer to returne backe, nor to recouer their former Priuiledges.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nec flagitium horum obliter abitur paenitentia;</hi> nor ſhall their foule offence bee put away by their pęnitence, or bee ſmoothed ouer with any cunning ſhadow of defence; for thoſe who haue fallen through infirmity or Error, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued vpon their repentance; but as for thoſe wicked ones, <hi>Qui fid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m quam Deo dedicauerint, polluerint, qui prodentes</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ide gloſſani ib.</note> 
                  <hi>diuinum myſterium, in prophana migrauerint, qui ſanctum Baptiſma prophanarunt, ijs nullo remedio penitentiae, (que ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let alijs criminibus adeſſ.) ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ccurritur;</hi> For thoſe, (I ſay) who haue falſified their Faith before dedicated to God, who betraying the Sacred myſteries of Chriſtianity, haue paſſed to prophane Hereſie, who haue prophaned their holy Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, they can haue no remedy by repentance, as other kinde of offenders receiue.</p>
               <p>They might not make a Will or Teſtament, they might neither ſell or bequeath ought, but their Goods were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed <note place="margin">Apoſtatarum.</note> on the next of their kindred, that were Chriſtians; and that by the Law.</p>
               <p>If any Maſter ſhould ſeduce vnto Hereſie any bond or Freeman, by compulſion or perſwaſion; <hi>Cum diſpendio for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunarum</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eum quicun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>capite pumendem eſſe cenſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mus</hi> they cenſured him <note place="margin">Eos qui Cathol.</note> to forfeit his Goods and his Life; (which Law I doe wiſh were in force among vs now alſo,) Clergymen and Moncks who forſooke the Orthodoxall Faith, and imbraced the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, and abhominable opinions of <hi>Apollinaris or Eutiches,</hi> were lyable to all the forenamed puniſhments, and moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer were baniſhed out the Roman Territories.</p>
               <p>In theſe pręcedent Authorities, wee hehold the practiſe of the Church in former Ages, againſt <hi>Apoſtaticall</hi> Miniſters; the effect whereof is as followeth:</p>
               <p>That what Prieſt ſoeuer, went out from the Church, and Ioyned himſelfe with Heretickes; but after renouncing his Hereſie, returned with a true penitent Heart, (which God ſeldome granteth vnto ſuch kinde of perſons) yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:21376:30"/>
hee could not bee admitted to the execution of his function in the Church againe; The which, were they in force in theſe dayes among vs, <hi>Rom</hi> ſhould haue little cauſe hereafter, to boaſt of the increaſe of her trayterous <hi>Proſelites;</hi> and the people who are like ſo many ſilly Sheepe, would be leſſe ſcandalized, and more ſafe from the danger of theſe bloody Romiſh rauening Wolues, who ſpare no coſt or tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, to Inuite them to relinquiſh the charge committed to their fidelity, that vpon their departure, and in their abſence, they may enter vpon the ſlocke, to ſcatter and deuoure it.</p>
               <p>And becauſe barking Dogs are moſt neceſſary for their pręſeruation; Therefore the Wolfe laboureth with all his craft, to enter league with the Dog, that he may ioyne with him, and cauſe him to reenter vpon them, to their vtter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
               <p>Such was the purpoſe of the <hi>Macedonian</hi> Prince, when hee demaunded tenne of the chiefe Orators of the <hi>A heni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> of which number, <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> ſhould bee one; on which condition, hee promiſed to raiſe his ſiedge.</p>
               <p>It ſeemed but a ſmall requeſt, in reſpect of the pręſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the whole Citty; but <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> the Prince of his profeſſion, who well foreſaw, what the euent would proue, diſcouered the damage, in this ſubſequent parable.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Wolues ſaid vnto the Shepheards, the onely cauſe of ſtrife betweene you and vs, are the Dogs; therefore to end the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> 
                  <hi>quarrell, giue vs your Dogs, and wee will be friends; which being performed, the Shepheards afterward being fallen a ſleepe; the Wolues ruſht in ſecurely, and deuoured cruelly, and in great aboundance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And no maruaile, ſeeing the Dog, which ſhould haue giuen warning of their approach, by barking, and haue repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led or deſtroyed them by byting, was at that time abſent, and out of the way.</p>
               <p>So if the Miniſters, whom the holy Scriptures in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, reſembleth vnto Dogs, depart from the people com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to their charge; The aduerſary hath free Ingreſſe left
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:21376:31"/>
vnto them, to deuour without controle; This was the poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique practiſe of that deteſtable <hi>Arrius,</hi> who that hee might make clearer paſſage for his blaſphemous Hereſie, laboured mainly, and at length wrought the Baniſhment of <hi>Arhana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Socrat. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Eccl. h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt. Cap.</hi> 23.</note> and of certaine of the ſtouteſt and moſt learned Biſhops who reſiſted him; But if they goe out to Ioyne with the Prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> and like <hi>Balaam</hi> bee drawen by reward, to curſe Gods people, whome hee hath bleſſed, they become more dangerous, and noyſome then the Enemy.</p>
               <p>And becauſe they betray the Goſpell of CHRIST ſitting in Heauen, they are little better in this, then their Father <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> the Traytor, who betrayed his perſon to his enemies the Iewes, when hee liued vpon Earth; and their Sinne being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, their cenſure ſhould not bee different, but the ſame; Therefore, <hi>let their dwelling bee Deſart, and let other take</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Act. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>their Office, and that without retractation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For thy cruelty againſt thy Brother</hi> Iacob, <hi>ſhame ſhall co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thee, and thou ſhalt bee cut off for euer,</hi> (ſaith God of <note place="margin">Abdias.</note> 
                  <hi>Edom.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whereby in an <hi>Allegory</hi> hee ſheweth that Haeretickes ought to bee cut off, for their cruelty againſt the Church, by corrupting the true Faith thereof, by renting the coate of the Spouſe, by labouring to deſtroy the Vineyard of the Lord of Sabaoth, by perſecuting, baniſhing, circumuenting the Miniſters thereof; by corrupting many of them, either by violence, or deceipt, or reward and promotion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O let the Children of Edom bee remembred in the day of Ieruſalem, how they ſaid; Downe with it, downe with it, euen</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 137.</note> 
                  <hi>to the ground: O Daughter of Babilon waſted with miſery; yèa happy ſhall he be, that rewardeth thee, as thou haſt ſerued vs; Bleſſed ſhall be bee that taketh thy Children, and throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them againſt the ſtones.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For why ſhould not wee bee as forward, to auenge the Truth againſt thoſe who Sinne of malitious wickednes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſame; As thoſe trayterous Apoſtates are earneſt to impugne the ſame, with the proude violence of the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:21376:31"/>
engines of falſhood; <hi>Therefore let their trauaile come on their owne head, and their wickednes fall on their owne pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſuch is their end for the moſt part; for as <hi>Iudas,</hi> after he had betrayed his Maſter with a kiſſe, hanged himſelfe, and thereby preuented his true repentance; So thoſe <hi>Iudas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Apoſtates,</hi> take away away hope of repentance from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, by <hi>Sinning directly againſt the knowne truth</hi> and their end is often deſpaire, or confounding ſelfe-will, obſtinacie, and periſh out of the Church, as it hath beene obſerued in all ages; yea it ſhould ſeeme, that God hath immediatly by his owne hand (according to their deſert) intercepted them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obſcrus Arrius</hi> that Monſter his filthy death, moſt fir for ſo wretched a Miſcreant; as he ſerued his body, his bowels <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ruff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>hiſt. Eccl. cap.</hi> 13</note> guſhed out.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ntanus</hi> began well, (as did <hi>Iudas)</hi> their end was not <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſeb. hb.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 14.</note> much different, he ſtrangled himſelfe, and <hi>Maximilla</hi> his Trull with a Halter; and <hi>Theodotus</hi> that begat this haereſie in them was ſo beſotted, that hee perſwaded himſelfe, hee ſhould be exalted, and aſſumed into Heauen, but in his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation into the ayre periſhed miſerably.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Neſtorius</hi> his tongue was eaten vp by the wormes, his <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Socrat. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 23.</note> ſeigned recantation eſpied, procured his deſerued depriua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and exile, whereas he dyed out of the Church.</p>
               <p>Though <hi>Marcion</hi> did publikely repent at <hi>Rome;</hi> yet was he receiued into the Church, but on condition, that is; if he <note place="margin">Tertul. lib. de pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſcript. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſus har.</note> reſtored and brought backe againe into the Church, thoſe whom he had before ſeduced; He was preuented by death, and not performing the condition, forfaited his peace.</p>
               <p>I could exemplifie the like in this laſt age, and that in many both domeſtick and forraigne, ſince the Church hath bin re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed; but I liſt not to plucke dead men by the beard; I haue onely annexed the Hiſtory of <hi>Francis Spiera,</hi> by way of an Appendix to this tractate; to reſtifie this truth in ſtead of the reſt.</p>
               <p>What? muſt all then periſh, the ignorant, as the learned? the weake as the ſtrong?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:21376:32"/>
I wiſh onely, that the Bondwoman were caſt out with her Baſtard;</p>
               <p>Farre be it from me, to murmure at the Church her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall clemencie, toward my brother who was once loſt, but hath returned againe: vniuſt indignation were that, which ſhould growe from my brothers ioyfull reconciliation; I mourne for their departure, and pray for their returne, who haue gone out from vs by <hi>Haereticall feduction,</hi> or haue bin ſeduced by a <hi>ſurreptitious error;</hi> or haue beene occaſionally carried away, by <hi>Terror and violent compuiſion;</hi> Let their vnfaigned penitence, with true humiliation, procure them indulgence, ſo they may truly pleade for themſelues, <hi>Simple ignorance and dreading infirmity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againſt thoſe onely, let it be an irreuocable Canon, and indiſpenſable decree, who haue gone out from vs <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Conc. Nio.</hi> Can. 11. Ioh 15.</note>, not through ſubtill ſeduction, or violent conſtraint, but of their owne peruerſe will; <hi>Let them be caſt out as dead branches, let them wither, let men gather them, and caſt them into the fire, and there let them burne with the firſt Apoſtata.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let no man obiect the lenity of the <hi>Councell of Nice to voluntary Reuolters;</hi> they held them <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <note place="margin">Vbi ſupra.</note> vnworthy of any fauour or humanity to be extended toward them; they enioyned them a <hi>three-fold pennanet,</hi> to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed for the ſpace of twelue yeares, without any mention of reſtauration to their holy function.</p>
               <p>Conceit it notwithſtanding, by way of implication; thou canſt not ſo ſhake off the bands.</p>
               <p>The Church tempered her Decrees, according to the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the Time; But heare what the <hi>Canon</hi> ſaith;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quod pro remedio ac neceſſitate temporis inſtitutum fuit, conſtat at primitus non fuiſſe; quod ergo neceſſitas pro remedio</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>q.</hi> 7. <hi>cap. quod pro romed.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>reperit, ceſſante vti<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> neceſſitate, debet ceſſare pariter quod vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gebat, &amp;c.</hi> A diſpenſation enforced by the neceſſity of the time, may not be obſerued as a common law that cannot be altered; for the cauſe which vrged being ceaſed, the diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation likewiſe muſt be voyde; for a lawfull order is one
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:21376:32"/>
thing, and an enforced vſurpation is another.</p>
               <p>Who did euer reade any auncient Canon, which receiued ſuch kinde of Apoſtates, who went out for ſome temporall commodity, or for aduancement to high dignity? Sure I am, I may vſe <hi>Auguſtine</hi> his words truly, of moſt of our perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Apoſtates;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Expertus credo multorum fict as poenitentias, per affectatas</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Diſt.</hi> 50. <hi>cap. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdos.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>honorum potentias;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Experience maketh mee confident to auerre, that many went out, in hope, they ſhould vpon their falſe repentance, be entertained into the Church, with ſome high preferment to an honourable office therein.</p>
               <p>They deceiue themſelues; The Church meaneth nothing leſſe; They may flatter themſelues with a vaine hope, to clime vp to the Pinnacle of the Temple; But let the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the end of <hi>Simon Magus</hi> quell their preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Thankes be vnto God, the Religious lawes of this land hath ſo prouided for them; let them therefore beware, leaſt ayming at the one vnaduiſedly, they be caught vp by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſeruedly, yea ineuitably; for, <hi>Quod non capit Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus, rapit fiſcus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I aduiſe them to be content with their entertainment at <hi>Rome,</hi> in the Temple of <hi>Dea Cloacina,</hi> whither (being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled by our Church) <hi>tanquam faeces et ſtercara,</hi> they haue betaken themſelues, euen to their <hi>vltimum refugium; A fit Cage, for ſuch vncleane Birdes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You expect a Reward for your pride, (for your pride I ſay) which begat in you <hi>Apoſtacie;</hi> for had you beene wiſe vnto Sobriety, and thought that of your ſelues which was meete, as your Brethren did; you had neuer forſaken vs; you know what that Truth (whom you haue forſaken) ſaith; That <hi>His Spirit ſhall reſt, Super humilem et quietum, et tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meniem</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eſay 66.</note> 
                  <hi>Sermones eius;</hi> Euen vpon him that is poore in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and of a contrite heart, and that trembleth at his words; So that the Spirit of verity dwelleth in the humble mind; but
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:21376:33"/>
hee forſaketh the Truth (of neceſſity) that deſpiſeth hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility.</p>
               <p>What wilt thou then ſay, that this ſeuerity is iniury? re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member alſo what thou haſt done againſt Chriſt; and thou ſhalt finde thy puniſhment farre more light then thy offence; Let S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Cyprian expoſtulate</hi> the matter with thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quod maius poteſt eſſe delictum, aut quae macula defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mior, quam aduerſeis Chriſtum ſtetiſſe?</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 1.</note>
               </p>
               <p>What greater offence can there be, or what fouler crime, then to take armes againſt Chriſt? then to ruinate his Church, which hee hath purchaſed and built with his owne blood? then to forget the peace, and loue of the Goſpel, and to make warre with furious hoſtility, againſt the quiet, louing, and peacefull people of God? In which reſpect the Canoniſt ſaid well; <hi>Non debemus dimittere in vltum opprobrium illius, qui probra noſtra deleuit;</hi> We muſt not leaue his diſgrace vnpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, <note place="margin">Hoſt. Sum. de Haeret. cap. qua poe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a feriatur.</note> who blotted out our ſhame.</p>
               <p>Remember what thou haſt done againſt his Church, which he ſo tendereth, that hee reputeth that iniurie which is done vnto it, as committed againſt himſelfe.</p>
               <p>It is <hi>crimen publicum;</hi> a publike offence againſt all, for that which is committed againſt the Truth of the Goſpell of <note place="margin">Cod. Tit. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n. chaeos.</note> Chriſt, <hi>in omnium fertur iniuriam,</hi> is an offence againſt all Chriſt his Members.</p>
               <p>Remember (I ſay) what thou haſt done againſt Chriſt his people, who being ſcandalized by thy departure, haue gone out after thee, being ſeduced by thee, and being preuented by death, haue happily dyed out of the Church, without the communication and peace of the ſame; whoſe Soules ſhall be required in the day of Indgement at thy hands, who haſt beene Author and cauſe of their deſtruction.</p>
               <p>In conſideration of which praemiſſes, I may inferre this concluſion, with <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in the like caſe;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qua propter, Iniquum put are noli, ſi perpetuo reijciaris;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Initio Statim. lib. de vtilit. credendi.</note> Wherefore do not think thy ſelf vniuſtly oppreſſed; if thou be reiected for euer, from the execution of that ſacred function.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:21376:33"/>
But ſuppoſe the Church ſhould open the boſome of her Piety to cheriſh thee; wouldeſt thou not like the vngrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Serpent, power forth thy poyſon into her bowels to her deſtruction?</p>
               <p>Pardon my Iealouſſy in this caſe; for it is not cauſleſſe, I may well vſurpe the ſaying of the great Father, in the ſame caſe, of his time; <hi>Quotidie cernimus, &amp; rebus probamus,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jeroni. in prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cip. cap.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp; in fiue cap.</hi> 12. <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>quod ideo Haeretici fidei ſimulent veritatem, vt ſimplices quoſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> decipiant, &amp; non ipſi conuertantur ad fidem, ſed fideles trahant adinfidelitatem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wee ſee dayly, and proue it true by experience, that Hę<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retickes diſſemble their returne to the true Faith, but onely that they may deceiue the ſimple credulous people; they come not as true Conuerts themſelues, but onely to drawe the faithfull to Infidelity; And there is no man ſo ſilly, but will confeſſe with <hi>Bernard,</hi> That a counterfeit cloſe Hęre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, is farre more peſtilent, then a profeſſed Hęreticke.</p>
               <p>Mine owne obſeruation in ſundry of this ſort, maketh me bolde to vrge that rule of the Law in this caſe; <hi>Semel malus, ſemper praeſumitur eſſe malus;</hi> hee that hath once played the traytor with <hi>Christ</hi> and his Church, will neuer bee true.</p>
               <p>I haue often grieued, to ſee the clemency of the Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed by them, and now I can containe my felfe in ſilence no longer, but that I muſt cry out with <hi>Cyprian;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Illud mirandum eſt imo indignandum potius &amp; dolendum,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſtianos Antichriſtis aſſiſtere.</hi> It is a ſtronge, yea a hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full rather and lamentable caſe, that Chriſtians ſhould aſſiſt Antechriſt, and that thoſe who decline from the Faith, and are traytors to the Church, ſhould in the Church, ſtand vp againſt the Church.</p>
               <p>For the pręuention of which miſchiefe, which might enſue vpon ſuch Diabolicall treachery; the rule of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Baſill,</hi> was in auntient times practiſed in the Church vpon ſuch perſons <note place="margin">
                     <hi>In Latinis, ea eſt Epiſt.</hi> 72.</note> as followeth:</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>Let them declare their penitence vnder the handwriting
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:21376:34"/>
and that they abhorre Hereticks, and that they are truely ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated from them; The like courſe alſo was vſed, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in ſucceeding Ages as is apparant in the <hi>Decrees col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by Gratian.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>queſt.</hi> 7.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Let <hi>Cyprian</hi> determine this point;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wee Decree</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>by conſent, and common Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that if any Prieſt or Deacon, who before receiued Sacred</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Orders in the Catholicke Church, and after ſtand out as Traytors and Rebels againſt the Church, or receiue prophane Ordination among Hereticks, from falſe Biſhops and Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts, contrary to the Order ſet downe by Christ; and there offer vp falſe and ſacrilegious Sacrifices; If they returne home againe, let them bee receiued on this Condition,</hi> Vt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municent Laici, <hi>to liue in the Church as Laymen; and let them thinke themſelues louingly dealt withall; that they are admitted to the peace of the Church, who before were enemyes of Peace; nor ought they at their returne, retaine thoſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes of Prieſthood and honour among vs, with which they haue rebelled againſt vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if the Religion and Doctrine of the Romaniſts be Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy; the Sinne of thoſe who embrace the ſame ſeemeth to bee little leſſe then hauing before profeſſed the Truth; and beene ſecured thereof, is Blaſphemy <hi>againſt the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> nor can they excuſe it, by ſaying they beleeue in the Creed and profeſſe Chriſt, their caſe you ſhall ſee reſembled in an authenticall Hiſtory.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mauia</hi> Queene of the <hi>Sarazens,</hi> inuaded and deſtroyed certaine Townes of <hi>Paleſtine</hi> and <hi>Arabia,</hi> in the Territories <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Secrat. lib.</hi> 4. Eccl. <hi>hiſt. cap.</hi> 29.</note> of the Roman Empire, nor would condiſcend to Peace, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe that <hi>Moſes</hi> a <hi>Sarazen</hi> (who led a Monaſticall life in the Deſert) a man greatly renowned, for his ſingular Piety, conſtant Faith, and ſtrange Miracles, were deſigned Biſhop of her Countrey. Vnto which the Roman Captaines gladly aſſented, and gaue charge it ſhould bee done with ſpeed; At length he was conueyed to <hi>Alexandria</hi> to receiue <hi>Sacred Orders;</hi> vnto whom when <hi>Lucius</hi> their Biſhop, an <hi>Arrian</hi>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:21376:34"/>
and cruell perſecutor of the Orthodoxall Chriſtians repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to conferre them; <hi>Moſes</hi> in the preſence of the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and people, who compelled him thereunto, ſaid; <hi>I thinke my ſelfe vnworthy of the Order of Prieſthood, yet if it bee thought Conducible to the Common-wealth; Tu</hi> Luci, <hi>manus mihi nunquam impones,</hi> Thou O <hi>Lucins</hi> ſhalt neuer impoſe thy handes on mee, which are full of the ſlaughter and blood of the Saintes; <hi>Lucius</hi> ſaid, hee ought not to charge him with ſuch ſhamefull deedes, but rather learne the principles of Religion of him, or as <hi>Ruffinus</hi> writeth, firſt <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>hiſt. Eccl.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Heare his Parth,</hi> and then <hi>Cenſure him accordingly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> anſwered, wee ſtand not now on the Articles of <hi>Religion;</hi> but your practiſes againſt your Brethren, <hi>Plane conuincunt, te vera Chriſtianae fidei dogmata non habere;</hi> Doe certifie that thou art deſtitute of the true Faith; for that ſtriketh not Chriſtians, doth not ſlay them, fighteth not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, for the ſeruant of the Lord ought not to fight.</p>
               <p>But thy deeds, which thou haſt done againſt them, whom thou haſt baniſhed, caſt vnto wilde Beaſts, to bee deuoured, whom thou haſt burned; As ſo many voyces cry out againſt thee, and thinges ſeene with our eyes are more certaine, then thoſe wee heare with our eares; I aſſure my ſelfe, that hee who beleeueth aright in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> would neuer doe ſuch thinges.</p>
               <p>So I ſay vnto all thoſe <hi>Apoſtates,</hi> who flye from the true Religion now profeſſed in <hi>England</hi> and elſe where, to the Synagogue of <hi>Rome;</hi> that howſoeuer they make an exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and generall profeſſion of the Faith of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> yet it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly appeareth by their particular <hi>Articles</hi> of Religion, that they worſhip not <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but their owne fictions, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they highly Blaſpheme him; <hi>For they are rauening Wolues in Sheepes cloathing, and the abhomination of Deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation ſtanding in the Holy place.</hi> They perſwade men that they beleeue in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and yet they labour to ſubuert the Faith, with the <hi>Engines</hi> of their <hi>Sophiſtry;</hi> they wreſt the Scriptures to their practiſe, and Inuent new Articles of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:21376:35"/>
Faith, and proclaime themſelues to haue the Truth in their Boſome, that in Imitation of <hi>Iudas,</hi> they may betray him with a kiſſe.</p>
               <p>But you ſhall know them better by their fruites; for the deedes which they haue done againſt the <hi>Saintes,</hi> and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of God, whom they haue baniſhed, Impriſoned, bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, hanged, tormented with ſtrange and vnheard Tortures, to make themſelues drunke with the blood of the <hi>Saintes,</hi> and with the blood of the Martyrs of IESVS, (that ſome of their owne Writers haue affirmed, that the <hi>Pope</hi> by reaſon of his cruelty, ſeemed rather to ſucceed <hi>Nero</hi> then <hi>Peter)</hi> Theſe deedes (I ſay) as ſo many voyces cry out at the Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy of them, who ſay they are <hi>Iewes,</hi> and are not; for if they were <hi>Abrahams ſonnes, they would doe the workes of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Apocalips 2.</note> Therefore they are the <hi>Synagogue</hi> of Sathan, for their workes beare witnes of them. <note place="margin">Ioh. 8.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Conſider this all yee, who worſhip the Beaſt and his I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, and receiue his marke on your forehead, or on your hand; <hi>Come out of her, that yee bee not partaker of her Sinnes,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Apocal. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>least yee receiue alſo of her Plagues;</hi> For the Lord hath ſaid, <hi>That ſuch ſhall Drinke of the Wine of his Wrath, yea of the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Cap. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>pure Wine, which is powred into the Cup of his wrath, and hee ſhall bee tormented in Fire and Brimſtone, before the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">14.</note> 
                  <hi>Angels, and before the Lambe; And the ſmoake of the torment ſhall aſcend euermore, and they ſhall haue no reſt, day nor night, which Worſhip the Beaſt and his Image.</hi> And whoſoeuer receiueth the print of his Name.</p>
               <p>Rememember thou <hi>Apoſtata, Whoſoeuer withdraweth</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>himſelfe from</hi> CHRIST, <hi>Gods Spirit hath no pleaſure in him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O bee not vngratefull to <hi>Chriſt;</hi> hee hath giuen him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for you; If any one ſhall maliciouſly defie IESVS, and perſiſt therein, hee hath Sinned <hi>againſt the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If hee worthily eſteeme not of his Paſſion, hee that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth another meanes of Saluation; ſaith, that the Blood of CHRIST, the Blood of the new Teſtament, the Blood
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:21376:35"/>
whereby hee is Sanctified, is polluted; Such a one reuileth the <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſay vnto you, that hee deſerueth farre greater torments; who deſpiſeth the Sonne of God now glorified; ſublimated aboue all Dignity of Superręſtiall eſſences, and placed in the Seate of his Fathers Maieſty; then the <hi>Iewes,</hi> who tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough Ignorance Crucified him, while hee was yet mortall; wee now know the Truth, therefore ſhall we bee vnexcuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, if wee deſpiſe ſo great Saluation.</p>
               <p>Of ſuch perſons ſaith <hi>Iob; What hope hath the Hipocrite,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Cap. 17.</note> when hee hath heaped vp his Riches, <hi>If God take away his Soule? Will God heare his cry, when trouble commeth vpon him? Will hee ſet his delight vpon the Almighty? Will hee call vpon God at all times?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As if hee ſhould ſay; The <hi>Hypocrite,</hi> whoſe Religion conſiſteth in the Seruice of <hi>Mammon;</hi> ſhall not bee able to ſtand in the Iudgement, nor will God heare him, when hee cryeth in diſtreſſe, nor can hee haue confidence in the Lord; becauſe hee is deſtitute of Faith, whereby wee haue peace with God, for which cauſe alſo, he cannot call vpon him by Prayer, and conſequently falleth into deſpaire; for ſuch commonly is the end of all <hi>Newters,</hi> and Diſſemblers in caſe of Religion.</p>
               <p>The which I will exemplifie in one Hiſtory of certaine truth, among many which I doe purpoſely omit, viz. of <hi>Francis Spiera</hi> an <hi>Italian,</hi> who to ſaue his Life and goods, fell from the <hi>Truth</hi> of the reformed Religion, which before hee had profeſſed; and therefore was ſo farre forſaken by God, that hee fell into deſperation, blaſpemed God, and (as the Story ſaith) hated him, and in that ſtate, departed out of this life; to the terror of all ſuch, who to purchaſe the Riches and Dignity of this world, forſake the Truth whereof they are aſſured, and profeſſe Popery, which is Doctrine of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils, to attaine promotion.</p>
               <p>For if this <hi>Italian,</hi> was ſo dreadfully puniſhed for that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, whereinto hee fell, through the infirmity of the Fleſh,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:21376:36"/>
for the pręſeruation of his life, (which otherwiſe ſhould haue periſhed) beſide his Poſſeſſions which were large; and the care of his Wife, and his Childten, who were many; (all which were ſtrong Motiues to fleſh and blood) yet God would not beare the mocke in this caſe.</p>
               <p>How much ſoarer puniſhment (thinke you) will hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict on thoſe, who, not by Compulſion, or feare of torments, forſake the Truth of the Goſpell, but onely like <hi>Demas,</hi> to enioy the pleaſures of this preſent world?</p>
               <p>The Hiſtory is recorded by a Learned man, as followeth in the next Leafe, which for breuity I haue ſomewhat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridged in this Tranſlation of it.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:21376:36"/>
            <head>THE HISTORIE FOL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LOWING IS RELATED OVT OF THE EPISTLE OF THAT FA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MOVS DOCTOR MATHEVV GRIBALDVS, Profeſſour of the Lawes, in the Vniuerſitie of Padua, <hi>who himſelfe was a Spectator of this lamentable accident.</hi> 1548.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is in the Territories of <hi>Venice,</hi> neere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Padua,</hi> a place called <hi>Citadella;</hi> wherein dwelt a Lawyer of good Iudgement; and great experience, named <hi>Francis Spiera,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout fifty yeares of age; married vnto a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous wife, by whom he had eleuen children, a man famous for his wealth and dignity.</p>
            <p>This man, began to embrace the Doctrine of the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Church, with incredible zeale; acknowledging <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> to be the onely Redeemer of mankinde, and profeſſed publikely with great conſtancie, that righteouſneſſe and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation was purchaſed by him alone, and that all mans workes, and Merites, (were in that reſpect) vaine and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable.</p>
            <p>For which cauſe he was accuſed to the Popes <hi>Legate</hi> at <hi>Venice;</hi> by whom he was cited to make his appearance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and menaced with death, and the confiſcation of his ſubſtance (which was great) wherewith he was ſo terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; that he renounced that truth, which he had profeſſed,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:21376:37"/>
and abiured it alſo; promiſing moreouer, that hee would make publike Recantation thereof, aſſoone as hee returned home; and ſo was diſmiſſed by the Legate.</p>
            <p>In his iourney homeward, hee was ouerwhelmed with a grieuous perturbation of minde, whither he ſhould embrace the Truth againe, or perſiſt in his deniall; yea, he often con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, that in his iourney, he felt the Holy Ghoſt vrge him, to profeſſe the truth conſtantly; But the fleſh, riches, and vaine pompe of this world ouerſwayed him.</p>
            <p>The day before he was to make his Recantation, a Popiſh Prieſt, brought the <hi>forme</hi> thereof vnto him; wherein hee ſhould publickly, in the open audience of the people, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce and condemne the Doctrine of the Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>That whole night, this wretched man ſpent without ſleepe; The morning following being Sunday, after Maſſe, in the preſence of his friends, of the Magiſtrates of the Towne, and in the aſſembly of the people, who were in number about 2000. He publikely renounced that truth, which he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore openly taught, and was fined 30. Duckets, which hee preſently payed downe.</p>
            <p>But ſuddainly after, hee felt the dreadfull Iudgement of God in his heart; hee was depriued of all the Guifts of the Holy Ghoſt, Chriſt departed from him; His heart was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed with meere hatred, enuie, and Blaſphemy againſt God; The Diuell, Death, and eternall deſpaire ſeaſed on him.</p>
            <p>After hee had beene thus tormented by the ſpace of ſixe Moneths; he remoued with his Wife and Children to <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dua,</hi> where his miſery encreaſed; He kept his bed being not ſicke; his reaſon and vnderſtanding alike as before his fall, he conſumed in his whole body, and all his Members (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide his tongue) languiſhed. He would admit no foode, but what was enforced; he kindly admitted all thoſe, who came to viſite him, and conferred very prudently with them; he affirmed, that he was damned by the iuſt iudgement of God; That hee was already in Hell, and was tormented with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:21376:37"/>
paines; that hee had ſinned againſt the Holy Ghoſt that his ſinne could neuer be forgiuen; hee ſaid that <hi>Chriſt</hi> his Merits, and Gods mercy, was for euer ſhut vp from him, and that this dreadfull end was brought vpon him, by the iuſt iudgement of GOD, to bee an Example to all the Elect.</p>
            <p>At length diuers learned, and graue Diuines repaired vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, propounding all meanes of Conſolation, eſpecially the greatneſſe of Gods Mercy.</p>
            <p>And though (ſaid he) I beleeue all that you haue rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, yet but as the Diuels, who beleeue and tremble; Hee ſaid, his Sinne was vnpardonable, that God ſecluded his mercy from him, that all faith was taken from him, that though he vttered the Lords prayer after them, yet his heart was full of hatred, malediction, and blaſphemy againſt God; for he knew how execrable he was with God, and that hee had taken away all his graces from him.</p>
            <p>The next day, they found his miſery augmented, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding how long his Conſcience had beene ſo tortured; he readily anſwered; That, gnawing worme, and vnquench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able fire, was ſent by GOD into his heart, ſince that day whereon he recanted the truth of the Goſpell, which before he profeſſed; So that now, his condition, was farre worſe then <hi>Cayns</hi> or <hi>Iudas,</hi> and that he had rather die and be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, then to be tormented in this life, with ſuch anguiſhes; adding farther, that he was already haunted with dreadfull apparitions, and helliſh viſions.</p>
            <p>Renewing their Conſolations, they intreated him to call vpon God in the Lords Prayer; which he performed with ſuch aboundance of teares, with ſuch ſighes, and ſo great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion of minde, that hee mooued the whole preſence to weepe; vpon which ſight, <hi>Doctor Gribaldus</hi> told him, that his teares argued, no totall deſertion by God.</p>
            <p>He anſwered, that he had not that faith, and truſt in God, which they ſuppoſed; for ſuch was the gift of God, whereof he was deſtitute;</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:21376:38"/>
Oh (ſaid hee) that GOD would vouchſafe mee this one gift, that I might feele in my heart, but the leaſt hope of his mercy, which is as vnpoſſible, as to vnlade all the water in the Ocean, with a Spoone.</p>
            <p>This I certainly know, that neuer mortall creature on the earth, felt the wrath of God, more manifeſtly then I doe; Oh that I might ſupply the roome of ſome other damned creature whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>So that all their comforts were vaine; They enforced Broathes into his mouth, to preſerue his life, his onely deſire was to die, and to be caried into Hell.</p>
            <p>Three dayes after; when among other learned men, <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius Fontanine,</hi> the <hi>Pryeſt</hi> of <hi>Citadell,</hi> (who bare him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany to <hi>Venice,</hi> when hee went vp to make his appearance before the Popes Legate) came to viſite him, and asked him, whether hee knew him; preſently vpon the remembrance thereof, with redoubled ſighes, and groones, he cryed out; Oh execrable day; oh curſed day; I wiſh I had neuer ſeene <hi>Venice,</hi> or that I had dyed, when I firſt intended my iourney thither.</p>
            <p>Then they commended the Merites of Chriſt vnto him; He ſaid, he neuer truly acknowledged the benefits of Chriſt, but abuſed them, and truſted too much to his carnall faith; (and turning to the Students) he ſaid;</p>
            <p>Oh my Sonnes; I will not detract from the Goſpell, I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it to be the Truth; but take heede, yee aſcribe not too much vnto faith, and neglect works beſeeming faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Chriſtians; Faith requireth this of vs, that wee be not Chriſtians in word onely. Giue credit vnto me, as vnto him; who hath truly tried the matter.</p>
            <p>Vpon this, he commended the Epiſtle of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peter,</hi> wherein he admoniſheth the faithfull, to <hi>Plety, Chaſtity</hi> and <hi>Sanctity;</hi> vpon which occaſion, they who were preſent, diſputed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably out of Gods word, and he liſtned as attentiuely.</p>
            <p>He was demanded, whither he receiued any comfort, by that godly conference; he anſwered, that he was damned to
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:21376:38"/>
euerlaſting death, neither was there any hope of Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion left for him; Oh (ſaid hee) that I could put the leaſt hope and truſt, in the mercy of God, and it would not be grieuous vnto me, to be tormented in the pit of Hell many Millions of yeares, ſo that I might haue any hope of deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
            <p>Whereupon, <hi>Doctor Gribaldus</hi> ſaid; Oh <hi>Francis,</hi> I am not deſperate of thy deliuerance; Happily it pleaſeth God, to make thee feele his wrath in this life, and in the life to come to ſhew thee his mercy.</p>
            <p>Hee anſwered, I doe certainly know that I am a Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gribaldus</hi> asked him, whither he would kill himſelfe, if a knife were deliuered vnto him, ſeeing he deſired ſo earneſtly to die; he ſaid; lend me one, and you ſhall ſee what I will doe; Notſo (ſaid <hi>Gribaldus)</hi> but declare thy minde wholy vnto vs; He anſwered, I know not the reaſon of my will or minde. <hi>Vergerius</hi> the Biſhop ſpent much labour in vaine to comfort him, and could hardly draw him to call vpon God in the Lords prayer; wherein though at length he aſſented vnto him, yet it was not done, with the like earneſt zeale as before; but he confeſſed that his minde was ſo alienated from God, that he could not call him Father.</p>
            <p>Hee entreated all that were preſent, that they would no longer ſpend their labour in vaine, in comforting him; for that all hope of obtayning Faith and Mercy at Gods hands, was cut off; So that it was more likely, that a Craine of Muſtardſeed ſhould fill vp the whole world, then that God ſhould giue him Faith and Grace.</p>
            <p>As hee was carried into a Horſelitter to be tranſported to <hi>Citadell,</hi> caſting about his eyes in a furious manner, by chance he eſpied a knife, whereon he laid hold, and had ſlaine himſelfe therewith; had not two of his Sonnes who were about him, wreſted it perforce out of his hands.</p>
            <p>Soone after, he died at <hi>Citadella.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the fearefull Hiſtory of <hi>Francis Spiera,</hi> which I
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:21376:39"/>
preſent to the conſideration of all ſuch, who thinke it a ſmall matter, to dally with Religion.</p>
            <p>I doe not ſay that hee was damned, neither doe I ſay that he was ſaued; howſoeuer; <hi>hee ſtandeth or hath fallen to his</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 14.</note> 
               <hi>owne Maſter;</hi> I will not preſume, to iudge another mans ſeruant; But I will take heede to my ſelfe, and aduiſe all my brethren to the ſame, leaſt that while wee thinke that wee ſtand, we ſhould fall; <hi>Let vs not be high minded,</hi> but feare; <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11. Rom. 11.</note> If he periſhed through vnbeliefe, was hee broken off? <hi>Tu autem fide ſta;</hi> Stand thou faſt by faith; if thou doeſt ſtand faſt, it is Gods mercy, not thy merit; for <hi>thou beareſt not the roote, but the roote thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly I will conclude, with a conſolation to all ſuch ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der conſciences, who are rapt into deſpaire, by giuing ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much eare, to the Soule ſlaughtering Doctrine of the auſtere <hi>Nouatians,</hi> and furious brainſicke <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> of our time.</p>
            <p>Who would perſwade that Repentance is not auaileable to thoſe, who fall into any notorious Sinne after Baptiſme, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aepin. Sup. Pſal.</hi> 9.</note> and hearty conuerſion vnto GOD? as if hee would by no meanes pardon the Repentant Soule; when as the Scriptures confirme in Doctrine, and examples, the contrary:</p>
            <p>As is manifeſt in <hi>Dauid,</hi> notwithſtanding his Adulterie <note place="margin">1. Sam. 12. Math. 9. Luk. 19. Gal. 1. Math. 26. 2. Chron. 33.</note> and Murther, in <hi>Mathew</hi> and <hi>Zacheus,</hi> though Vſurers and Extortioners; In S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul,</hi> though he perſecuted the Church; In S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peter,</hi> though he denied <hi>Chriſt,</hi> with Imprecations and Oathes; and aboue all in <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> though he fell away from God, and followed all the abominations of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and vſed Witchcraft and Charming, and Sorcerie, and familiar Spirits, and Southſayers; Yet when hee humbled himſelfe, and prayed vnto the Lord: The Lord was entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by him, and heard his prayer, and forgaue him his ſinne.</p>
            <p>Heare the Lord himſelfe; <hi>As I liue (ſaith hee) I deſire not the death of the wicked, but that hee turne from his way,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 33.</note> 
               <hi>and liue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If thy Sinne be <hi>Great,</hi> his Mercie and Goodneſſe is <hi>Grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> If thy Sinnes be <hi>Many, according to the Multitude of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 51.</note>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:21376:39"/>
               <hi>his mercies, he will doe away thine affences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Were thy Sin more weighty the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth, then the Sea, hee who created theſe, can peize thy Sinne, and <note place="margin">Rom. 5.</note> 
               <hi>where Sin hath abounded, cauſe grace much more to abound.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though thou fall backe neuer ſo often, through infirmity; yet he is Almighty, and both can, &amp; will raiſe thee vp againe, if thou put thy truſt in him; <hi>For who ſo putteth his truſt in the Lord, mercy embraceth him on euery ſide.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 31.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Excellently ſpake <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> againſt the <hi>Nouatians;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apud Chytr. Sup cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Apccalyps.</hi>
               </note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,</p>
            <p>Though thou fall backe neuer ſo often, through Infirmity, yet vpon hearty Repentance, thou ſhalt be receiued; and no leſſe comfortably S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auguſtine; Toties apparet opus Dei</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>miſerentis, quoties fit confeſſio poenitentis;</hi> God doth as often take compaſſion, as the penitent Sinner maketh his confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <hi>Magnitudinem morbi vides, Medici potentiam non vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des;</hi> If thou art terrified by the greatneſſe of thy Sinne, yet <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt. Sup. Pſal.</hi> 55.</note> be comforted by the power of the Phyſitian.</p>
            <p>When thou art in greateſt deſpaire, <hi>Grata ſuperueriet quae</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 68.</note> 
               <hi>non ſperabitur hora,</hi> God will come vnto thee in an houre, when thou lookeſt not for him, hee will bring thee from the deepe of the Sea.</p>
            <p>Hee calleth as well in the laſt houre as in the firſt; I will iudge no man, I will deſpaire of no man, I will pray for all men; while Gods patience in this life leadeth them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</p>
            <p>A man (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine)</hi> may be a <hi>Pagan</hi> to day, an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleeuing <hi>Iew</hi> to day, an <hi>Haereticke</hi> to day; a <hi>Schiſmaticke</hi> to day; <hi>Quid ſi cras amplectatur Catholicam fidem? &amp;c.</hi> What if the next day, hee doth embrace the Catholick faith, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. apud Lumb.</hi> 1. <hi>Sent. diſt.</hi> 43.</note> and follow the Catholicke truth? What if ſo be thoſe whom thou doeſt ſee, tainted with any kinde of Error, and doeſt condemne them as moſt deſperate fellowes, ſhould repent before they end this life, and finde true reſt, and life in the world to come?</p>
            <p>Iudge no man before the time therefore.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:21376:40"/>
I know not why any man ſhould deſpaire, ſeeing <hi>God is louing, true, and powerfull;</hi> but that we may be confident in him (with the holy Father) becauſe of the <hi>Truth of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> 
               <hi>the loue of his Adoption, and the Ability of his perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pater eligit, filius diligit, Spiritus Sanctus coniungit et vnit;</hi> The <hi>Father</hi> hath choſen vs, the <hi>Sonne</hi> loueth vs, the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cyprian. Ser. de Baptiſma Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti. tom.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> ioyneth and knitteth vs vnto God; who then ſhall be able to ſeparate vs from the loue of Chriſt? <hi>I am perſwaded that neither death, nor life, nor Angels, nor prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> 
               <hi>nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature ſhall be able to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate vs from the loue of God, which is in Chriſt Ieſus our Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I conclude the whole, with the words of our Sauiour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All ſinnes ſhall be forgiuen vnto the children of men, and Blaſphemies wherewith they blaſpheme; But he that blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Mark. 3.</note> 
               <hi>againſt the Holy Ghoſt, ſhall neuer haue forgiueneſſe, but is culpable of eternall damnation;</hi> from the which Sinne, <hi>God</hi> keepe vs in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> our onely <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Sauiour;</hi> To whom with the <hi>Father,</hi> and the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> be aſcribed praiſe, and glory, and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and thankes, and honor, and power, and might, for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21376:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
